<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter sent to a friend containing some reflections upon a late book intituled, The Roman church vindicated, and M.S. convicted of a false witnesse against her Wherein is declar'd, that the Pope may excommunicate and depose Kings according to the judgement of their greatest doctors, decrees and practices of several Popes, and Canons of their most approved councils; and the author convicted of most notorious falsities, &amp;c. By J.S. B.D.</title>
            <author>Stopford, Joshua, 1636-1675.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 105 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61683</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5743</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222081</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833311</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833311</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37787</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61683)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37787)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2064:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter sent to a friend containing some reflections upon a late book intituled, The Roman church vindicated, and M.S. convicted of a false witnesse against her Wherein is declar'd, that the Pope may excommunicate and depose Kings according to the judgement of their greatest doctors, decrees and practices of several Popes, and Canons of their most approved councils; and the author convicted of most notorious falsities, &amp;c. By J.S. B.D.</title>
                  <author>Stopford, Joshua, 1636-1675.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 33, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Anti-Catholicism --  England --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37787:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> A LETTER SENT TO A FRIEND Containing ſome Reflections upon a late Book Intituled, The Roman Church Vindicated, and M. S. Convicted of a falſe Witneſſe againſt her.</p>
            <p>Wherein is declar'd, That the Pope may excommunicate and Depoſe Kings according to the Judgement of their greateſt Doctors, Decrees and Practices of ſeveral Popes, and Canons of their moſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved Councils;</p>
            <p>AND The Author convicted of moſt notorious Falſities. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>By J.S. B.D.</p>
            <p>PRINTED In the Year 1675.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:37787:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37787:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:37787:3"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37787:3"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>ABout three Months ago, I heard of an Anſwer to my Book, ſent from Prieſt to Prieſt for their Aſſiſtance and Approbation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 'twas committed to the Preſs. This News, ſeconded with the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ictoria's</hi> of ſome <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> might well put ſuch a <hi>Freſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water Souldier,</hi> as I am, into a ſad pickle. But when the Book was publiſhed, and I had caſt an eye upon the very firſt Page, where I found theſe comfortable Expreſſions: <hi>That the</hi> Eagles <hi>of their Church ſcorn'd ſuch a</hi> Flye, <hi>and that the uncivilized</hi> Popiſh Prieſts <hi>would not vouchſafe to requite me with Ink and Paper;</hi> nay, <hi>that I was fallen into the hands of a poor home-bred Country-man, who inherits his Mothers Compaſſionate Care for all that are in a longing Condition</hi> (as he perceived I was, and yet no <hi>Pope Joan,) and that can willingly part with a piece of his Heel to do them good.</hi> p. 2. I ſay, the peruſal of theſe words ſo farre cheared me, that I could not but ſmile, when I had read a little further, and came to that <hi>general</hi> Stop <hi>which he put to my</hi> Foord, (moſt wittily alluding to my Name) with three or four falſe <hi>Quotations</hi> out of <hi>Luther, Whitaker, Stil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingfleet</hi> &amp;c. After this, I proceeded to the Body of his diſcourſe, ſtuffed with various <hi>Citations,</hi> all which, though true and pertinent, make very little againſt me; Yet, having already diſcover'd him to be a true <hi>Son</hi> of the <hi>Roman Church</hi> (one that will ſay any thing for the Honour of his <hi>Holy Mother)</hi> I reſolved to examine thoſe Authors, and ſee, whether they do really affirm what they are urged for, in the Places cited by him. This I have done with great care and diligence, and can aſſure you, that moſt of his <hi>Quotations</hi> are abſolutely falſe, or wholly impertinent. But I'le come to particulars.</p>
            <p>In his firſt <hi>Chap.</hi> he endeavours to vindicate the <hi>Roman Church</hi> from all <hi>Treaſonable Doctrines,</hi> in confuting this Poſition; <hi>That the Pope hath power to excommunicate and depoſe Kings, and abſolve their Subjects from their Allegiance to them.</hi> And for this the <hi>Canons</hi> of <hi>Councils, Decrees</hi> of <hi>Popes,</hi> and the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of a few <hi>Doctors</hi> are urged by him.</p>
            <p>He begins with the <hi>Canons</hi> of ſeveral <hi>Councils</hi> viz. 4, 5, 6. and 10. of <hi>Toledo,</hi> the <hi>Council of Conſtance, Aquiſgrane—.</hi> and very confidently tells his <hi>Reader, That theſe are a ſufficient evide<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce of their Church's Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and enough to convince me of my blindneſs,</hi> in aſſerting, <hi>That the</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:37787:4"/> 
               <hi>Pope hath power to excommunicate and depoſe Kings.</hi> Were this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man as dexterous in proving, as he is confident in affirming, certainly the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> never had a more worthy <hi>Champio<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the <hi>Councils</hi> of <hi>Toledo</hi> three things may be offer'd, which not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly weaken, but quite deſtroy the <hi>Authority</hi> of them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Where doth he find, that the <hi>Pope</hi> called theſe <hi>Councils,</hi> preſided in them, and gave them his <hi>Bleſſing,</hi> I mean, Confirmed them. And you know without theſe, Eſpecially the two Latter, they were no more then a few private <hi>Doctors;</hi> and conſequently their <hi>Decrees</hi> not to be accounted the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Beſides, in the greateſt of theſe <hi>Synods,</hi> we find not above 70 <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Preſbyters</hi> in and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to <hi>Spain.</hi> And that theſe, or at le<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt their immediate <hi>Succeſſors</hi> were none of the moſt profound <hi>Divines,</hi> is clear from the eight <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Toledo,</hi> where <hi>Can.</hi> 4. they Decree, <hi>That Biſhop<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall not marry;</hi> and urge theſe Scriptures 1 Pet. 1. 15. <hi>Be ye holy, as I am holy.</hi> and Col. 3. 5. <hi>Mortifie your members, which are on the Earth.</hi> And yet theſe Scriptures are as much againſt the <hi>Marriage</hi> of <hi>Prieſts,</hi> as Rom. 8 8. <hi>They that are in the fleſh cannot pleaſe God,</hi> once urged by <hi>Pope Siricius.</hi> Epiſt. 4. And <hi>Can.</hi> 9. they Decree, <hi>That no man ſhall eat fleſh in Lent,</hi> and give theſe moſt powerful Reaſons. 1. <hi>Becauſe the forty dayes of Lent, are the Tithes of all the dayes of the Year; and the Tithes ſhould be conſecrated to God.</hi> 2. <hi>Becauſe, that Chriſt by faſting forty dayes, expiated the Sinnes of Mankind.</hi> If ſo, to what end did he ſuffer death? 3. <hi>Becauſe 'tis conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient that Man, made of four Elements, for breaking the ten Precept of the Decalogue, ſhould afflict his body four times ten dayes.</hi> By theſe <hi>Reaſons</hi> you may judge of the Learning of that <hi>Age.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Theſe <hi>Places</hi> are not full to the point; for the Queſtion is, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Pope in certain Caſes, may not depoſe Kings, and abſolve their Subjects from their Allegiance?</hi> And all that theſe <hi>Councils</hi> ſay, is, <hi>That whoſoever ſhall go about by any means of Conſpiracy, to violate the Oath of his Fidelity, which he hath taken for the preſervation of his Country, or the Kings life; or who ſhal attempt to lay violent Hands upon the King, or deprive him of his Kingly Power—let him be accurſed in the ſight of God.</hi> But when the <hi>Pope</hi> hath excommunicated and depoſ'd a Prince, he ceaſes to be a Prince, his Subjects are abſolv'd from their Oath, and may, if Commiſſion'd by his <hi>Holineſs,</hi> lay violent hands upon him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Moſt unfortunately hath he mention'd the 4 and 6 <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Toledo.</hi> Had he read them, and underſtood the <hi>Hiſtories</hi> of thoſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:37787:4"/> 
               <hi>Times,</hi> certainly he had paſſed them over. For in the 4. <hi>Council,</hi> thoſe Biſhops and Presbyters acknowledge <hi>Siſenan<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us,</hi> or <hi>Siſnandus</hi> for their King, who had rebell'd againſt <hi>Suintila,</hi> or <hi>Suinthila,</hi> their lawful Soveraign. <hi>Grimſton Hiſtory of Spain,</hi> lib. 5. p. 146. 147. <hi>Rodericus Hiſtor. Hiſpan. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 176. And as if this were not ſufficient they denounce Curſes againſt any that ſhall endeavour to diſtu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>b him, <hi>Can.</hi> 74. Not 47. as he found it quo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed. Thus you ſee, he urgeth a vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of <hi>Treaſon</hi> and <hi>Rebellion,</hi> to be the Doctrine of their Church for <hi>Loyalty</hi> and <hi>Obedience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the 6. <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Toledo</hi> Can. 3. they Decree, <hi>That no man ſhould be tolerated to dwell in the Kingdom of</hi> Spain, <hi>who did not profeſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Catholick Faith; and that Kings in all times to come, before they were placed in their Royal Seat, ſhould be bound, by the Obligation of a Solemn Oath, to interpoſe their Authority, that this Act might be obey'd: Otherwiſe the King, refuſing to put this Act in execution, ſhall be</hi> Anathema Maranatha <hi>in the ſight of God, and become Fewel for the everlaſting Fire; and likewiſe all that joyn with him.</hi> This plainly ſhews in what ſence, and with what limitations the <hi>Canon</hi> he mentions, is to be underſtood; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently how little it makes for, nay, how much againſt his preſent pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. Can we imagine theſe <hi>Doctors</hi> to Decree <hi>Loyalty</hi> and <hi>Rebellion</hi> with the ſame breath?</p>
            <p>And to as little purpoſe is the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Conſtance</hi> urged; for many of their <hi>Doctors</hi> (more likely to underſtand the ſenſe of it, than a <hi>poor home-bred Country-man)</hi> tell us, <hi>That 'tis to be underſtood of a private Perſon before Sentence is given.</hi> Suarez defenſ. Fidei Cathol. lib. 6. cap. 4. Azo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius Inſtit. Moral. Tom. 2. lib. 11. cap. 5. Quaeſt. 10. Gregor. de Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentia Tom. 3. Diſput. 5. Quaeſt. 8. Cardinal Perrons <hi>Oration to the third Eſtate of</hi> France, with many others. And <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat this is the ſence of that <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil,</hi> is ſufficiently clear from her own words, which this <hi>Gentleman</hi> hath moſt prudently, but knaviſhly, paſſed over. The words are theſe; <hi>Non expectata ſententia, vel mandato Judicis.</hi> So that all which the <hi>Council</hi> condemns, is, That Tyrants may be lawfully and deſervedly killed by any of their Subjects, <hi>non expectata ſententia</hi> &amp;c. before the Judge hath paſſed Sentence, or given his Command for it: which is no more, than what thoſe <hi>Doctors,</hi> which are moſt Zealous for the <hi>Popes</hi> depoſing faculty, do every where aſſert, and urge many arguments for. And if you deſire to know, what was the occaſion of this <hi>Decree,</hi> I muſt refer you to our learn'd King <hi>James in his Defence of the right of Kings</hi> p. 459—whoſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:37787:5"/> 
               <hi>Hiſtorical Account</hi> my deſign'd Brevity will not permit me to tranſcribe.</p>
            <p>In the next place <hi>(p.</hi> 29.) he tells his Reader, that the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Aquiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grane</hi> under <hi>Ludovicus Pius,</hi> and that of <hi>Rhemes</hi> ſpeak to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: But whether he means the firſt or ſecond of <hi>Aquiſgrane,</hi> both which were held under <hi>Ludovicus Pius:</hi> or the firſt, ſecond, third, or fourth of <hi>Rhemes,</hi> he, <hi>not out of an averſion from being too bulkiſh and tedious,</hi> but for other weighty reaſons, very wiſely leaves us to conjecture. The two Synods of <hi>Aquiſgrane,</hi> and the firſt of <hi>Rhemes</hi> I have met with in <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> and cannot find any thing in them pertinent to his purpoſe.</p>
            <p>After theſe <hi>Councils</hi> he muſters up <hi>(p.</hi> 34.) a few <hi>Doctors; Covarruvias, Navar, Salmeron Aquinas—</hi>all which either affirm the contrary to what they are urged for, or fay nothing to the purpoſe. <hi>Covarruvias</hi> aſſerts, <hi>That the Pope hath truly a temporal Power over Emperours, ſo farre as it may be profitable and neceſſary to the Government of the Church, and uſe of the Spiritual Power.</hi> apud Bellarm. contra Barclaium p. 21. <hi>Navar.</hi> affirms <hi>That the Pope may depoſe Kings, that are negligent in governing their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, whereby they are kept from the attainment of eternal life.</hi> Comment. ad Cap. Novit. de Judiciis Notab. 3. n. 99. <hi>Salmeron,</hi> in thoſe <hi>Places</hi> cited by him, ſayes nothing to the purpoſe, and elſewhere maintains the contrary, Tom. 13. lib. 1. part. 3. diſput. 12. <hi>That if a King be an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick, or a favourer of Heretickes, he may be juſtly depoſed.</hi> Nay <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min</hi> himſelfe muſt ſpeak for him, <hi>de Rom. Pontif. lib.</hi> 5 <hi>cap.</hi> 2, 3, 4. which diſcovers, that either this <hi>Gentleman</hi> never read <hi>Bellar.</hi> or doth not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand him. And as little to the purpoſe is <hi>Sylveſters</hi> Teſtimony. p. 41. <hi>That none are oblig'd to obey the Popes Commands (even under pain of excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) when thoſe that are ſo commanded, know his Commands to <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e unjuſt;</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he tel us (as indeed he ſeems to do) that <hi>Sylveſter</hi> deny'd this do<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rine: But this great <hi>Divine</hi> and learned <hi>Canoniſt</hi> is a zealous <hi>Aſſerter</hi> of it. <hi>The Pope may excommunicate an Emperour, that is worthy of Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and depoſe him that is worthy of depoſition.</hi> Again, <hi>The Pope hath an univerſal Juriſdiction</hi> (over all Chriſtian Kings and Princes) <hi>in Spirituals and temporals.</hi> Again, <hi>He can dep<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe for a reaſonable cauſe.</hi> In Summa. ve<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bo. Papa. num. 11.</p>
            <p>From theſe <hi>Doctors</hi> he proceeds <hi>(p.</hi> 41.) to their <hi>Popes,</hi> and very grave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tells us; <hi>All thoſe Popes, whom vertue confin'd to the Primitive Rule, have taught us Reverence and Loyalty to our temporal go<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s by their own Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: and ſome of them have upon occaſion committed their faithful Thoughts to Writing for the I<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtruction of Poſterity.</hi> And here he inſtanceth firſt in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:37787:5"/> Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> 3<hi>-who being conſulted in a temporal Affair by a Subject of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">* <hi>This Pope excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated &amp; depoſed the Emperour</hi> Otho, <hi>and <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>r King</hi> Iohn.</note> 
               <hi>France return'd Anſwer,</hi> That he ſhould make his Addreſs to his King, who had no Superior in Temporal Cauſes. <hi>apud Bellarm. de Rom. Pontif. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. But this is not only impertinent, but abſolutely falſe; as any one may ſee, that will caſt his eye upon <hi>Bellarmin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, but Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the great will do his work, whom he brings in uttering theſe words: <hi>That though he was furniſhed with all temporal Power to have revenged the grievous Oppreſſions, wherewith the Princes of Lombardy afflicted the Church for thirty five y<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ars; yet was he over ſwayed by the fear of God, to decline all violent defence, and recurre to that Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Refuge of Prayers and tears, as the ſole Means of the Churches Redreſſe.</hi> Epiſt. 1. ad Sabian. diacon. Epiſt. 45. (43 it ſhould have been) ad Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam Imperator. But in the firſt there's not one <hi>Jota</hi> to the purpoſe: And in the ſecond no mention that <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Tears</hi> are the ſole means of the Church's Redreſs.</p>
            <p>Then, to prove that the Roman Church never claimed or knew of any temporal Sword, or Prince-depoſing Authority, he brings in Pope <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>colas Cauſ.</hi> 33. <hi>Quaeſt.</hi> 2. <hi>Cap. Inter haec.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But there he ſpeaks of <hi>Husbands</hi> killing their adulterous <hi>Wives,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns it; for (ſaith he) <hi>Dei Eccleſia mundanis nunquam conſtringitur: Gladium non habet niſi ſpiritualem.</hi> And the <hi>Gloſs</hi> hath theſe words: <hi>Gladium quoa executionem. Hoc ideo dico, quia Imperator habet illud a Papa.</hi> That is, The Church can only excommunicate <hi>Offenders;</hi> Temporal Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments muſt be inflicted by the <hi>Civil Magiſtrate.</hi> Then he brings in Pope <hi>John</hi> 8. <hi>Cauſ.</hi> 16. <hi>Quaeſt.</hi> 3. <hi>cap. porro.</hi> But here we have not one word to the purpoſe; for that Pope only ſaith, <hi>That Clergy-men may not put on Armour, and fight againſt their Enemies; ſince Prayers and Tears are their Armour.</hi> So the <hi>Gloſs</hi> expounds it. Then comes in Pope <hi>Celeſtin</hi> 3. <hi>Extravagant. de Judiciis. Cap. Cum ab homine.</hi> But I cannot find any ſuch <hi>Chap.</hi> or any ſuch thing aſſerted by him. Thus far he hath not brought one true and pertinent <hi>Teſtimony</hi> either from their Doctors, Popes, or Councils. In his <hi>(p.</hi> 44) he tells us, <hi>That Lewis</hi> 12. <hi>in a Council at Tours, had the Reſolution of all the French Biſhops, that he might contemn the Popes unjuſt Cenſures. And that the Doctors of Sorbon condem<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed this Poſition:</hi> That the Pope hath power to puniſh Princes with temporal Penalties, and caſt them out of their Kingdomes <hi>p.</hi> 50—. And theſe <hi>viz.</hi> The determinations of a few <hi>French Biſhops,</hi> and the <hi>Sorbonne Doctors,</hi> he makes the moſt fundamental <hi>Decrees</hi> and <hi>Doctrines</hi> of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, <hi>p.</hi> 54. But to theſe I anſwer.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:37787:6"/> 1. In other Points, when we urge ſeveral <hi>Councils</hi> againſt them, their uſual <hi>Plea</hi> is, that either they were but <hi>Provincial,</hi> or not confirmed by the <hi>Pope;</hi> and therefore no <hi>Doctrines</hi> of the Church: But here (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this <hi>Gentleman)</hi> a few <hi>Biſhops</hi> in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Doctors</hi> of <hi>Sorbonne,</hi> have power to make moſt fundamental <hi>Decrees</hi> and <hi>Doctrines,</hi> without the <hi>Popes</hi> Approbation, nay, againſt his expreſs Will.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We find the <hi>French Biſhops,</hi> and <hi>Sorbonne Doctors</hi> aſſerting the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary <hi>Doctrine.</hi> In the year 1589, the <hi>Leaguers</hi> propounded two <hi>Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions</hi> to the <hi>Doctors</hi> of <hi>Sorbon.</hi> 
               <q>1. Whether the People of <hi>France</hi> may not be diſcharged from the Oath of Allegiance made to <hi>Henry</hi> 3? 2 Whether the People may with a ſafe Conſcience take up Arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him? And, after earneſt <hi>Prayers,</hi> that the Spirit of God would direct them, a ſolemn <hi>Maſs,</hi> and moſt diligent diſcuſſion of the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>‡de Serres p.</hi> 870. <hi>* And that the greateſt part of the Clergy of</hi> France <hi>were of the ſame judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, will not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd by any that hath look't into their Hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torians.</hi>
                  </note> Points, they anſwer. 1. That <hi>Henry</hi> both by the <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Po<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fical</hi> Law is fallen from his dignity. 2. That the People of <hi>France,</hi> may lawfully fight againſt him. 3. That theſe <hi>Decrees</hi> be ſent to the <hi>Pope</hi> for his Confirmation. <hi>Boucher de juſta Henrici</hi> 3. <hi>abdicatione.</hi> And accordingly a Letter was drawn up and ſent to <hi>Rome,</hi> in which they moſt humbly beſeech his <hi>Holyneſs</hi> for three things. 1. That they may be declar'd abſolved from their Oath to <hi>Henry</hi> 3. 2. That he would decree the War juſt, which they had undertaken againſt that <hi>Oppreſſor</hi> of Publick Religion and Liberty. 3. That in this neceſſary Work, he would aſſiſt them with his <hi>Prayers</hi> to God Almighty, and with a <hi>Jubile</hi> of <hi>Indulgence,</hi> that others thereby might be provoked to joyn with them, <hi>Idem p.</hi> 393.</q> To which the good old <hi>Gentleman</hi> return'd a very gracious Anſwer, and for their greater encouragement iſſued out his <hi>Bull</hi> againſt King <hi>Henry,</hi> and all his <hi>Adherents Idem p.</hi> 403. And this <hi>Author</hi> tells us <hi>(p.</hi> 377) the <hi>Faculty</hi> of <hi>Sorbon</hi> had done no more, than what is incumbent on <hi>Lawyers, Confeſſors, Pariſh Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Doctors,</hi> who ought to aſſert and vindicate the power and dignity of the <hi>Roman See.</hi> Upon the publiſhing of this <hi>Bull,</hi> the people were greatly encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged in their <hi>Rebellion</hi> againſt their <hi>Soveraign</hi> whom they no more call <hi>King,</hi> but only <hi>Henry de Valois, Heretick Tyrant,</hi> and what not? Nay, they <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut him out of the <hi>Canon,</hi> and declared it unlawful to pray for him in Publick. <hi>Boucher. p.</hi> 380. And this Author <hi>(p.</hi> 418) informs us, <hi>That ſo wonderfully powerfull was this Bull againſt</hi> Henry <hi>and his Adherents, that by a Miracle one at</hi> Venice <hi>(but offering to ſpeak in behalf of the King) ſunk preſently down, and no ſooner was carried home, but he died.</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:37787:6"/> And a little after, the ſame <hi>Doctors</hi> return'd theſe <hi>Anſwers</hi> to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <note place="margin">
                  <hi>de Serres. p.</hi> 894.</note> 
               <hi>Quaeries</hi> in reference to <hi>Henry</hi> 4. their lawful King. <q>1. That all Catholicks by Divine Law are forbid to admit any into the Throne, that is an Heretick, or a favourer of Hereſy. 2. That thoſe who favour the ſaid <hi>Henry,</hi> are deſerters of Religion, and continually in a mortal ſin: ſo thoſe, who for love to their Religion do oppoſe him, do very much merit both of God and Men. And as on the one hand, thoſe who aſſiſt the King, will be Eternally damned; ſo on the other hand, 'tis moſt meet to conclude, that they, who are ſlain in this Cauſe againſt the ſaid <hi>Henry,</hi> ſhall obtain an eve<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>laſting Reward, and be crowned with the Trophies of Martyrdom. See them at large in Mr. <hi>Foulis Hiſtory of Romiſh Treaſons &amp;c. p.</hi> 566.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But about 4 years after, when the King had vanquiſh'd the <hi>Leaguers,</hi> and entred <hi>Paris,</hi> thoſe <hi>Sorbon Doctors</hi> change their Note, make void all former <hi>Decrees,</hi> and profeſs great Zeal and Loyalty to King <hi>Henry</hi> 4. Idem <hi>p.</hi> 591.</p>
            <p>And what was the <hi>Opinion</hi> of their Biſhops—in <hi>Lewis</hi> 13. time, is clear from this following <hi>Story. Lewis</hi> 13. being come to his <hi>Majority,</hi> ſummoned the three <hi>Eſtates</hi> to meet: Two of them <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Clergy</hi> and <hi>Nobles,</hi> preſently concluded, <q>
                  <hi>That the Council of</hi> Trent <hi>ſhould be publiſhed, and received in</hi> France. But the third <hi>Eſtate</hi> made this <hi>Decree:</hi> That his Majeſty ſhal be humbly deſired, that it may be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by the three Eſtates for a fundamental Law; That, the King being acknowledged Head in his Dominions, holding his Crown and Authority only from God, there's no Power on Earth whatſoever, Spiritual or Temporal, that hath any Right over his Kingdom, either to depoſe our Kings, or diſpence with, or abſolve their Subjects from the Fidelity and Obedience, which they owe to their Soveraign, for any cauſe or pretence whatſoever. This ſtartles the <hi>Clergy</hi> who with the <hi>Nobles</hi> ſet themſelves againſt the third <hi>Eſtate,</hi> with a Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to quaſh their Loyal Deecre. And to effect this, they deſired Cardinal <hi>Perron</hi> (a man of great Eloquence and Learning) to diſcuſs the Point in an Oration to the third <hi>Eſtate.</hi> This Cardinal (being attended with ſome Lords and Biſhops, as Repreſentatives of their reſpective Eſtates, and to ſignify that he ſpake not only his own, but their Opinions too) went to them; where he made a very long <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>And the Pope gave him thanks for his Speech, if K.</hi> James <hi>may be credited. p.</hi> 383.</note> Speech to ſhew the unreaſonableneſs and abſurdity of the foreſaid Propoſition; endeavouring to prove by Reaſon, that ſometimes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:37787:7"/> Kings ſhould, and by Example, that ſometimes they had been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed.</q> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>He affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that this was the current doctrine in</hi> France <hi>till the time of</hi> Calvin. <hi>And for the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry doctrine viz.</hi> That Kings are not depoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by the Pope, <hi>He calls a D<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine that bre<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ds Shiſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns; a Gate that leads into all Hereſy; and to be held in ſo high a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation, that rather then yield to it he and his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops would chuſe to burn at a Stake.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sir,</hi> By this you ſee, how <hi>Romiſh Doctors</hi> can alter their Judgements, and preach contrary Doctrines, according to the preſent Exigency of Affairs; <q>This Cardinal <hi>Perron</hi> (ſaith our King <hi>James</hi> p. 386) was a Follower of <hi>Henry</hi> 4. even when depoſed by the <hi>Pope;</hi> and in a certain Aſſembly holden at the <hi>Jacobins</hi> in <hi>Paris,</hi> he withſtood the Popes <hi>Nuntio</hi> to his face, when the ſaid <hi>Nuntio</hi> labour'd to make this Doctrine touching the Popes temporal Soveraignty paſs for an Article of Faith. But in this Speech to the third Eſtate, he confidently affirms, that whoſoever maintains this Doctrine to be wicked, that Popes have power to depoſe Kings, they teach men to believe, that there hath not been any Church for many Ages paſt, and that the Church is the very Synagogue of Antichriſt. Herein hath he very wel acommoda<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed himſelf to the Times. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </q> And that ingenuous <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>feſſion</hi> of the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> in <hi>Paris</hi> is obſervable. The <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> having cenſur'd <hi>Anto<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ius Sanct<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rellus</hi> his Book (which was printed at <hi>Rome</hi> by Pe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>miſſion of the Super<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ours, and Approbation of <hi>Vitel<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcus</hi> General of the Jeſuits) ſent for theſe Gentlemen, and demanded, Whether they believ'd as their: General did, concerning this Book? They anſwered, that their General living at <hi>Rome,</hi> could not but ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove that, which was agreeable to the Court of <hi>Rome.</hi> But being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain demanded, what they believed? Anſwered, that they believed the clean contrary. Being again askt, And what would you do, if you were at <hi>Rome?</hi> Anſwer'd, as they do at <hi>Rome.</hi> Which made ſome of the Court ſay, <hi>Have theſe Men one Conſcience at</hi> Rome, <hi>and another at</hi> Paris? <hi>God keep us from ſuch Confeſſors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, if we look back to Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> 4. his time, we ſhal find the <hi>Biſhope,</hi> and other <hi>Clergy-men</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> in a Council at <hi>Lyons,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring for the Popes Authority to depoſe Emperours—. But more of this after wards. Thus you ſee, how Zealous even the <hi>French</hi> have been (when they ſaw it was convenient) in aſſerting the Popes depoſing fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty; and conſequently the imprudence of our <hi>Adverſary,</hi> in urging this Teſtimony of the <hi>French Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Sorbonne Doctors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will paſs over the <hi>Petition</hi> of our Engliſh Catholicks in King <hi>Charles</hi> 1. his Reign <hi>p.</hi> 59. in which they make Solemn proteſtations of Loyalty (for ſuch <hi>Stuff</hi> will not paſs with thoſe, that know their <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,</hi> or have read the <hi>Declaration</hi> made to King <hi>James,</hi> even when they were plotting his ruin in the <hi>Gun-powder Treaſon;)</hi> As alſo the great
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37787:7"/> 
               <hi>Braggs</hi> he makes of their Loyalty in the late times of Rebellion <hi>p.</hi> 63. For I know you have read, <hi>The late Apology in behalf of the Papiſts, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd in behalf of the Royaliſts printed</hi> 1667. <q>Who tels them, that in <hi>Ireland</hi> there were whole Armies of <hi>Iriſh</hi> and <hi>Engliſh,</hi> that ſought againſt his Majeſty, ſolely upon the account of their Religion. That in <hi>England</hi> ſome came in voluntarily to aſſiſt him, but many more of them were hunted into his <hi>Garriſons,</hi> by them that knew they would bring him little help, and much hatred. And of thoſe that fought for him, ſo long only as his Fortune ſtood; when that once declined, a great part even of them fell from him. From that time forward, they that were alwayes deemed <hi>Cavaliers,</hi> where were they? In all thoſe weak <hi>Efforts</hi> (1647. 1656. 1659) of gaſping <hi>Loyalty,</hi> what did they? They complyed, and flattered, and gave Sugar'd words to the <hi>Rebels</hi> then, as they do to the <hi>Royal<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſts</hi> now. They addreſt their <hi>Petitions</hi> to the Supream <hi>Authority</hi> of this Nation, the <hi>Parliament</hi> of the Commonwealth of <hi>England.</hi> They affirm'd, that they had gener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally taken, and punctually kept the <hi>Ingagements.</hi> They promiſed, that if they might but enjoy their <hi>Religion,</hi> they would be the moſt quiet and uſeful <hi>Subjects</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> And this they proved by real Teſtimonies; which we have no pleaſure in remembring, and they would have leſs in hearing of them. <hi>p.</hi> 14.</q> Are not theſe <hi>Petitions</hi> and <hi>Profeſſions</hi> moſt convincing demonſtrations of <hi>Catholick Loyalty?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus, <hi>Sir,</hi> you ſee, how unſuccesful this <hi>Gentleman</hi> hath been in his firſt Attempt; what pitiful Witneſſes he hath brought to convict this <hi>Poſition</hi> of falſhood <hi>viz. That the Pope hath power to depoſe Kings, and abſolve their Subjects from their Allegiance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before I paſs to his next <hi>Chap.</hi> give me leave to produce ſuch Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, for your further ſatisfaction in this <hi>Point,</hi> as no <hi>Romaniſt</hi> can in reaſon and Conſcience except againſt: And theſe are, the <hi>Opinions</hi> of their greateſt <hi>Doctors, Decrees,</hi> and <hi>Practices</hi> of ſeveral <hi>Popes,</hi> and <hi>Canons</hi> of their moſt approved <hi>Councils.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That the <hi>Pope</hi> hath power to excommunicate and depoſe <hi>Kings,</hi> and abſolve their <hi>Subjects</hi> from their Allegiance, is moſt clear from the <hi>Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions</hi> of their greateſt <hi>Doctors.</hi> And here, <hi>Sir,</hi> I will refer you to Mr. <hi>Foulis</hi> (knowing you have the Book) who hath amaſſed together about three hundred <hi>Cardinals, Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, School-men, Canoniſts, Hiſtorians—</hi>that aſſert and maintain this Doctrine. <hi>Hiſtory of Popiſh Treaſons p.</hi> 41—. Some of theſe Authors I have (which I find faithfully quoted)
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37787:8"/> and could add others to the Catalogue. I know this <hi>Gentleman</hi> ca<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them <hi>Brethren of iniquity, p.</hi> 36. <hi>Idle wranglers, p.</hi> 47. <hi>aſpiring Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, p.</hi> 56, <hi>ſeeming Members, p.</hi> 58. But let him ſhew me, when and where they were condemned, what <hi>Index Expurgatorius</hi> has cenſured them. Nay, if he deal honeſtly, he cannot but confeſs, that theſe <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors</hi> are generally approved, and had in great admiration among them, that are the <hi>Guides</hi> of Lay-mens Conſciences. But on the other hand, I find ſeveral, who have oppoſ'd this <hi>Doctrine,</hi> cenſur'd, and their Books condemned by the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Take a few Inſtances.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Petrus de Vineis,</hi> who collected the Epiſtles of <hi>Frederick</hi> 2. Emperour of <hi>Germany,</hi> which contain a Defence of the Imperial Lawes againſt the Popes Uſurpations. <hi>William Occam,</hi> and <hi>Marſilius</hi> of <hi>Padua,</hi> who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the ſame Rights in behalf of the Emperour <hi>Lewis</hi> 4. <hi>Antonius de Roſellis</hi> of the Power and Authority of the Pope, who writ upon the ſame occaſion in behalf of the Emperor <hi>Frederick</hi> 3. <hi>Cardinal Zabarel</hi> of of Schiſmes, which ſhould be taken away by the Emperors Authority. The <hi>Monarchy</hi> of <hi>Dantes,</hi> who affirms that the Emperour depends not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Pope, but holds his Empire from God. A <hi>Diſpute</hi> betwixt the <hi>Clerk</hi> and the <hi>Souldier,</hi> containing a Defence of the Royal Lawes of the Kings of <hi>France</hi> againſt the Popes Uſurpations. They have not ſpared <hi>Pope Pius</hi> 2. though he declar'd in his <hi>Bull,</hi> all that to be heretical, which he had written againſt the Popes Authority, when he was called <hi>Aeneas Sylvius.</hi> The Speech of <hi>Anthony Arnald</hi> in the Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>John Chaſtel,</hi> who attempted to murder the King. <hi>Congregat.</hi> 10. <hi>Roger Widdringtons</hi> Apology againſt <hi>Bellarmin. Congreg.</hi> 12. And his <hi>Theological Diſputation</hi> concerning the Oath of Allegiance. <hi>Congreg.</hi> 13. <hi>God and the King.</hi> Congreg. 16. The <hi>Explication</hi> of the Oath of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, called <hi>Zentum ad Catholicos Anglos.</hi> Congreg. 24. <hi>Scutum Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium,</hi> i. e. againſt all King-killers, and their Patrons. <hi>Congreg.</hi> 25. <hi>William Barclay</hi> of the Pope's Power. <hi>Congreg.</hi> 10. But moſt ſevere they are upon our King. <hi>James</hi> his <hi>Apology</hi> for the Oath of Allegiance, <hi>Congreg.</hi> 8. <q>This Book, they ſay, contains pernicious and execrable Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, contrary to the Truth and purity of the Holy Catholick Fa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th. And all Perſons are prohibited to read or keep it, upon pain of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication (from which they cannot be abſolv'd but by the Pope) and the <hi>Mulct</hi> of a thouſand <hi>Ducats.</hi>
               </q> Some of theſe (with many more, which I have no time to mention) were cenſur'd by the Council of <hi>Trent;</hi> and others by the <hi>Pope, Cardinals,</hi> &amp;c. authorized thereunto by that Council. <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 25. <hi>ſub. ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:37787:8"/> 2. From the <hi>Decrees</hi> and <hi>Practices</hi> of their <hi>Popes.</hi> From their <hi>Decrees</hi> and <hi>Conſtitutions. Gregory</hi> 1. gave great Priviledges to S. <hi>Medard</hi> in <hi>Soiſſons,</hi> with an expreſs Order, <hi>That the King or Potentate ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graded or depoſ'd, that did violate them.</hi> This is urged by <hi>Suarez, Bellar. Azorius—</hi>for the Popes Depoſing Faculty. <hi>Baronius</hi> glories much in it. <hi>anno</hi> 593. <hi>n.</hi> 86. And <hi>Gregory</hi> 7. made uſe of it, to juſtify his Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of <hi>Henry</hi> 4. Emperor of <hi>Germany.</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>Bellarmin con<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ra Barcla<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um p.</hi> 308. <hi>Becanus Controv. Angl. p.</hi> 128. Let all know, that they are abſolv'd from their Fidelity and Allegiance to thoſe, that are fallen into He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy, notwithſtanding all former Oaths and Promiſes made unto them. <hi>Decret. Gregor. Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Tit.</hi> 7. <hi>cap</hi> 16. <hi>Boniface</hi> 8. decreed; That the Church hath two Swords, Spiritual and Temporal; that the Spiritual Power may inſtitute and judge the Temporal, according to that of <hi>Jeremy; Behold, I ſet thee over the Nations, and over the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, to root, out, and to pul down</hi> &amp;c. And he declares it neceſſary to ſalvation, for every Humane Creature to be ſubject to the Roman Biſhop. <hi>Extrav. Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Tit.</hi> 8. <hi>Cap.</hi> 1. We obſerving (ſaith <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> 7.) the <hi>Decrees</hi> and <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> of our Holy Predeceſſors, do ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve all from their obedience to Excommunicate Perſons, whereunto they were formerly oblig'd by Oath or any other way; and do ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly charge them, that for the future they yield no Allegiance to them.</q> 
               <hi>Decret.</hi> 2. <hi>pars. Cauſ.</hi> 15. <hi>Quaeſt.</hi> 6. <hi>Cap.</hi> 4. And the like <hi>Decree</hi> we find in the next <hi>Chap.</hi> made by <hi>U<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ban</hi> the ſecond.</p>
            <p>To theſe I will add the <hi>Bull</hi> or <hi>Breve</hi> of Pope <hi>Paul</hi> 5. againſt our <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Allegiance;</hi> in which he declares. <q>That they cannot, without moſt evident and grievous wronging of Gods Honour, bind themſelves by that <hi>Oath.</hi> And afterwards, That it cannot be taken with ſafety of the <hi>Catholick Faith,</hi> and of their ſouls health; ſince it containeth many things, that are plainly and directly contrary to <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi>
               </q> And Pope <hi>Urban</hi> 8. in his <hi>Bull</hi> ſent to the Catholicks in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> 1626. calls it, <hi>That pernicious and unlawful Oath of Allegiance.</hi> And a little after tells them: <hi>That which our Predeceſſor</hi> Paul 5. <hi>with ſo great deliberation decreed, that ought ye altogether to obſerve as a Decree of Truth.</hi> And again, <hi>Sonner ought the Sword of the Migh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y take from a Chriſtian his Life, than his Faith:</hi> Implying, that a man loſes his <hi>Faith,</hi> when he takes this <hi>Oath.</hi> And yet our King <hi>James</hi> hath told the World, <q>How careful he was, that nothing ſhould be contained in it, except the Profe<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ion of Natural Allegiance, and Civil and Temporal Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:37787:9"/> with a promiſe to reſiſt all contrary uncivil Violence.</q> 
               <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitory Preface to all Chriſtian Monarchs.</hi> p. 292. Thus I have clear'd the Propoſition from the <hi>Canons</hi> and <hi>Decrees</hi> of ſeveral Popes; which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by that much admired Council of <hi>Trent Seſſ.</hi> 25. <hi>Cap.</hi> 20. <q>Wherefore it decrees and commands, that the Sacred <hi>Canons,</hi> and a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l <hi>General Councils,</hi> together with other <hi>Apoſtolical Sanctions,</hi> made in favour of Eccleſiaſtical Perſons and Eccle<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iaſtical Liberty, and againſt the Violators thereof (all which it renewes by this preſent Decree) be preciſely obſerv'd by all men.</q> This, you ſee, comprehend, all their <hi>Canons, Decretals, Clementines, Extravagants, Bulls—.</hi> 
               <q>And they are ſworn unto by every <hi>Prieſt</hi> at his <hi>Ordination,</hi> according to the <hi>Bull</hi> of Pope <hi>Pius</hi> 4. I vow and ſwear true <hi>Obedience</hi> to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> the <hi>Succeſſor</hi> of Saint <hi>Peter Prince</hi> of the Apoſtles, and <hi>Vicar</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt. And all other things do I undoubtedly receive and confeſs, which are delivered, defined, and declared by the Sacred <hi>Canons</hi> and <hi>General Councils</hi> &amp;c.So help me God.</q> 
            </p>
            <p>And the <hi>Practices</hi> of ſeveral <hi>Popes</hi> have been agreeable to theſe <hi>Decrees</hi> and <hi>Conſtitutions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gregory</hi> 2. rebell'd againſt the Emperor <hi>Leo Iſaurus,</hi> and made <hi>Rome</hi> and the <hi>Roman Dutchy</hi> to do the ſame; becauſe he prohibited the adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Images. <hi>Bellar de Roman. Pontif. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. <hi>Azorius Juſtit. Moral. Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 1669. <hi>Sigonius Hiſtor. de Regno Ital. p.</hi> 103.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gregory</hi> 3. with the Conſent of the <hi>Roman Clergy,</hi> deprived <hi>Leo</hi> 3. Emperor of <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> becauſe he had taken Images out of Churches. <hi>Platina in vit. Gregor. Azorius Inſtit. Moral. Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 1610.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pope Z<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>chary</hi> abſolv'd the people of <hi>France</hi> from their Allegiance to <hi>Childerick</hi> their King, and depoſed him. <hi>Bellar de Roman Pontif. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap</hi> 8. <hi>Azorius Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 1669. <hi>Perrons</hi> Oration to the third <hi>Eſtate</hi> of <hi>France.</hi> That Pope <hi>Zachary</hi> only conſented to <hi>Childerick's</hi> depoſition (as this <hi>Gentleman</hi> affirms <hi>p.</hi> 43.) is moſt falſe; which <hi>Bellarmin</hi> proves from the <hi>Annals</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> and the Teſtimony of <hi>Eginarthus, Aimonius, Rhegino, Lambertus Schaph<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aburgenſis, Sigebertus, H<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rma<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nus, Mar<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us Scotus,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Contra Barclaium p.</hi> 318—.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Steven</hi> 2. ſet on <hi>Pepin</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> to expel the <hi>Exarchs</hi> out of <hi>Italy,</hi> and obtained of him the <hi>Exarchat</hi> for himſelf, which belong'd to th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Emperor of <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtantinople, Platina.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Leo</hi> 3. tranſlated the Empire from the <hi>Greeks</hi> to the <hi>Germans. Bellar. de Rom. Pontif. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 8. <hi>Boucher de juſta Henrici</hi> 3. <hi>abdicatione p.</hi> 17. <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons Oration.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:37787:9"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Gregory</hi> 7. excommunicated <hi>Henry</hi> 4. Emperor of <hi>Germany,</hi> and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated the Empire to <hi>Rodulph</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxony. Platina. in vit. Bellar. de Rom. Pont. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 8. <hi>Azorius Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 1610. And give abſolution of all their ſins to thoſe, that adhered to <hi>Rodulph,</hi> and oppoſed <hi>Henry. Baronius</hi> an. 1080. <hi>Sect.</hi> 12. The ſame Pope excommunicated and depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Boleſlaus</hi> 2. King of <hi>Poland. Azorius Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 1669. <hi>Boucher. p.</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Urban</hi> 2. excommunicated and perſecuted <hi>Henry</hi> 4. Emperor of <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. Platina in vit. Urbani.</hi> The ſame Pope excommunicated and depoſ'd <hi>Ph<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lip</hi> 1. King of <hi>France. Bellar. Contra Barclaium p.</hi> 29. <hi>Matth. Paris an.</hi> 1095.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paſchal</hi> 2. made the Son of <hi>Henry</hi> 4. Emperor of <hi>Germany,</hi> to take Arms againſt his Father, and depoſ'd him in a <hi>Synod</hi> held at <hi>Mentz</hi> by the Popes command for that purpoſe. <hi>Aventinus Annal lib.</hi> 5. And he commanded <hi>Robert</hi> Earl of <hi>Flanders</hi> to deſtroy the Clergy of <hi>Cambray</hi> and <hi>Liege;</hi> becauſe they adhered to <hi>Henry</hi> 5. And he was to do it for the remiſſion of all his ſins. <hi>Bochel decret lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 6. <hi>de Paſcal. &amp; Leod.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adrian</hi> 4. excommunicated <hi>William</hi> King of <hi>Sicily,</hi> and abſolved his Subjects from their Allegiance to him. <hi>Platina in vit. Becanus Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ. Angl. p.</hi> 107.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexander</hi> 3. excommunicated <hi>Frederick</hi> 1. Emperor of <hi>Germany,</hi> and perſwaded the Towns of <hi>Italy</hi> to rebel againſt him. <hi>Platina in vit. Alex.</hi> This Pope excommunicated <hi>William</hi> Duke of <hi>Apul<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a,</hi> and engaged the foreſaid Emperor to fight againſt him, to gain that <hi>Dukedom</hi> to the Chair of Rome. <hi>Platina ibid.</hi> And the ſame Pope excommunicated and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſ'd <hi>Frederick</hi> 2. Emperor of <hi>Germany Platina ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Celeſtin</hi> 3. gave <hi>Conſtantia</hi> a Nunne to <hi>Henry</hi> 6. Emperor of <hi>Germany,</hi> and gave him for her <hi>Dowry</hi> the Kingdom of both the <hi>Sicilies,</hi> upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition he ſhould expel <hi>Tancred,</hi> who oppoſed his Election. Hereu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on a bloody War aroſe between thoſe two Princes. <hi>Platina in vita Celeſt.</hi> And he excommunicated <hi>Phil. Auguſtus Boucher p.</hi> 210.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Innocent.</hi> 3. excommunicated the Emperor <hi>Otho</hi> 4. and depriv'd him of the Empire. <hi>Platina in ejus vita. Bellar. de Sum. Pontif. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 8. <hi>Azorius Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 1610. And the ſame Pope deprived our King <hi>John,</hi> and provoked his Subjects to rebel againſt him. <hi>Azorius Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 1669. and gave to <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>France</hi> the remiſſion of all his ſins upon condition of invading and conquering <hi>England. Matth. Paris p.</hi> 232. <q>Where the Story is thus related: The Pope by the Counſel of the Cardinals,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37787:10"/> Biſhops, and other prudent men, gave a definitive Sentence, that the King ſhould be depoſed; And for the execution of that Sentence, the Pope writ to the moſt Potent King of the French, <hi>Philip,</hi> that for the remiſſion of his ſins, he ſhould take that labour upon him.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Honorius</hi> 3. and <hi>Gregory</hi> 9. excommunicated and depoſ'd <hi>Frederick</hi> 2. Emperor of <hi>Germany,</hi> and raiſed ſeveral Rebellions againſt him. <hi>Platina in vit. Honor. &amp; Greg. Matth. Paris in Henrici</hi> 3. <hi>Angl. vita.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Innocent</hi> 4. excommunicated and depoſ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d the ſame Emperor, <hi>Platina in vit. Innocent. Bellar. lib</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 8. And the ſame Pope excommunicated and deprived <hi>Conrade</hi> Emperor of <hi>Germany. Matth. Paris p.</hi> 825.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Urban</hi> 4. prevailed with <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Anjou</hi> to invade <hi>Sicilie,</hi> and deprive <hi>Manfred</hi> the King. <hi>Onuphrius Annotat. in Platin. p</hi> 214.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gregory</hi> 10. promoted the Rebellion of <hi>Michael Palaeologus</hi> againſt <hi>Baldwin</hi> 2. Emperor of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and gave him the Empire. <hi>Bozius de Jure ſtatus lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap. p.</hi> 287—.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Martin</hi> 4. depoſed <hi>Peter</hi> King of <hi>Arragon,</hi> and abſolv'd his Subjects from their Allegiance to him. K. <hi>James</hi> his Works. <hi>p.</hi> 397. <hi>Becanus Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trov. Angl. p.</hi> 107.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Boniface</hi> 8. ſubjected <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> and his Kingdom to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror <hi>Albert. Azorius Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 1663. And <hi>Platina</hi> gives this Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of him: <hi>That he ſtudied to give terror rather than Religion unto Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors, Kings, Princes, and Nations; and labour'd to give and take away Kingdomes according to his pleaſure.</hi> In vit. Bonif.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John</hi> 22 or 23. excommunicated <hi>Lewis</hi> 5. Emperor of <hi>Germany,</hi> and depriv'd him. <hi>Platina.</hi> And <hi>Benedict</hi> 12. did the ſame. <hi>Platina</hi> in <hi>vit. Joh. &amp; Benedict.</hi> And the like was done by <hi>Clement</hi> 6. <hi>Platina. Azorius Tom. p.</hi> 1610. And he excommunicated all the Biſhops, that adhered to him, and fixed Bulls on all the Churches doors to raiſe Rebellion againſt h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Julius</hi> 2. excommunicated <hi>Lewis</hi> 12. of <hi>France,</hi> and gave his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to the firſt Conqueror. <hi>De Serres p.</hi> 560. He excommunicated the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>netians,</hi> and gave their Dominions to any, that would take them. He excommunicated the Duke of <hi>Ferrara,</hi> and invaded his Country by Arms. <hi>De Serres.</hi> And he excommunicated the King of <hi>Navar,</hi> and gave his Kingdom to the King of <hi>Arragon,</hi> who thereupon invades and takes it. <hi>Azorius Tom.</hi> 2. p. 1670. <hi>Guicciardin lib.</hi> 11. <hi>p.</hi> 444. <hi>Onuphrius in ejus vita.</hi> 'Tis thought he was the death of two hundred thouſand Chriſtians in ſeven years time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pius</hi> 5. iſſued out a <hi>Sentence Declaratory</hi> againſt Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> wherein her Subjects are declar'd abſolv'd from the Oath of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:37787:10"/> and every thing due unto her, and thoſe that adhered to Her, are involv'd in the <hi>Anathema Sanders de Schiſmate Anglican<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 815. <hi>de Viſib. Monarch. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi> 706. Hereupon a <hi>Rebellion</hi> was deſign<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d. <hi>Sanders ibid. Felton</hi> who fixed this <hi>Declaratory Sentence</hi> of the Pope upon the Biſhop of <hi>Londons</hi> Gates, and ſuffer'd for it, is accounted a glorious Martyr. <hi>Sanders de Viſib. Monarch. p.</hi> 710. And ſo is the Earl of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberland,</hi> who hereupon raiſ'd a <hi>Rebellion,</hi> and was executed for it at <hi>York. Sanders de Schiſm. Angl. p.</hi> 310.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixtus</hi> 5. excommunicated <hi>Henry</hi> 3. of <hi>France,</hi> and all his Adherents. <hi>Cicarella in vita Sixti. Boucher. p.</hi> 403. This Pope excommunicated the King of <hi>Navarre,</hi> and abſolv'd his Subjects from their Allegiance, <hi>Cica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rella ibid.</hi> And <hi>Gregory</hi> 14. ſent great Summes of Money into <hi>France</hi> to pomote the Rebellion of the Leaguers. <hi>Cicarella in vit. Greg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> 5. excommunicated the Duke and Senate of <hi>Venice,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd them of their Priviledges. <hi>Bzovius in vit. Pauli.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> 3. iſſued out a thundering Bull againſt our <hi>Henry</hi> 8. in which he deprives him of his dominions. <hi>Onuphrius in ejus vita.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this <hi>Catalogue</hi> of excommunicated and depoſed Princes, we might add <hi>Sanctius</hi> King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> who left his Kingdom by the Command of <hi>Innocent</hi> 4. <hi>Greg. Tholoſanus de Repub. Lib.</hi> 26. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> King of <hi>Hungary</hi> depoſed by <hi>Alexander</hi> 5. ibid. <hi>Ferdinand</hi> deprived of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Naples</hi> by <hi>Innocent</hi> 8. ibid. <hi>Georg. Pogebracius</hi> King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by <hi>Paul</hi> 2. ibid. <hi>Deſiderius</hi> King of <hi>Lombardy</hi> excommunicated by Pope <hi>Adrian. Becanus Controv. Angl. p.</hi> 107. <hi>Rogerius</hi> King of <hi>Sicily</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated by <hi>Innocent</hi> 2. ibid.</p>
            <p>Here, <hi>Sir,</hi> you have above forty <hi>Emperors, Kings,</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated and depoſ'd by <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhops; and yet this <hi>Country-Gentleman</hi> hath the confidence to tell us <hi>p.</hi> 45. <hi>That the Popes are few that can be juſtly taxed with this over-reach of due limits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. I will now in the laſt place produce their moſt approved Councils for the further confirmation of this truth. If Practice may be admitted to ſpeak in this Point (which with our <hi>Romaniſts</hi> is none of the weakeſt Arguments) we ſhall find that Princes may be lawfully depoſed, and that confirm'd by the Grandeur of ſuch Meetings. <hi>Gregory</hi> 7. in a Synod at <hi>Rome,</hi> in which Arch-biſhops, Biſhops, Abbats, and an infinite number of the Clergy were preſent, ſolemnly excommunicated and depoſed <hi>Henry</hi> 4. Emperor of <hi>Germany. Baronius an.</hi> 1080. <hi>Sect.</hi> 16. And this Decree or Sentence was confirm'd by <hi>Gregorie's</hi> Succeſſors in ſeveral
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:37787:11"/> Councils. By <hi>Victor.</hi> 3. in a Council at <hi>Beneventum. Leo Oſtienſis in Chronico Caſſinenſi lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 7<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. By <hi>Urban</hi> 2. in a Synod at the ſame place, <hi>an</hi> 1091. <hi>Bertoldus Conſtantienſis.</hi> In another Synod at <hi>Placentia</hi> before an innumerable Multitude. <hi>an.</hi> 1095. And the ſame year in another at <hi>Claremont Matth. Paris ad an.</hi> 1095. <hi>p.</hi> 22. By <hi>Paſchal</hi> 2. in a general Council at <hi>Rome</hi> an. 1102. <hi>Abbas <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſpergenſis.</hi> By <hi>Gelaſius</hi> 2. in a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil at <hi>Cologne. Idem an.</hi> 1118. By <hi>Calliſtus</hi> 2. in a Council at <hi>Rhemes,</hi> in which 400. Fathers were aſſembled. <hi>Abbas <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſperg. Sugerius in Vita Ludo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vici Reg. Francon. Rogerius in Annal. Angl.</hi> All which we have atteſted by their great <hi>Bellarmin contra Barclaium p.</hi> 108—. <hi>Alexander</hi> 3. in a Synod at <hi>Claremont</hi> excommunicated <hi>Frederick</hi> 1. Emperor of <hi>Germany, Platina in vit. Alex.</hi> And <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> 2. did the like to <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>France</hi> in a Council held at the ſame place. <hi>Spondanus.</hi> p. 969. And <hi>Innocent</hi> 4. in a Council held at <hi>Lyons,</hi> excommunicated <hi>Frederick</hi> 2. Emperor of <hi>Germany.</hi> and abſolv'd his Subjects from all Homage and Fealty due unto him. And further declar'd, <hi>That if they for the future own'd him for their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, or any other aſſiſted him, they were</hi> ipſo facto <hi>involved in the ſame Curſe.</hi> Sexti Decret. lib. 2. Tit. 14. cap. 2.</p>
            <p>I will paſs by other Inſtances of this nature, and proceed to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of their General Councils, which juſtify ſuch ſevere proceedings againſt Kings and Princes. <hi>Gregory</hi> 7. in a Council at <hi>Rome</hi> with the conſent of thoſe Fathers made this Decree; <hi>That it was in the Pope's power to depoſe Emperors, and abſolve Subjects from Obedience to their Princes.</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronius, <hi>an.</hi> 1076. <hi>Sect.</hi> 31. In the <hi>Lateran</hi> Council under <hi>Alexander</hi> 3. we find it decreed. <q>That the Subjects of Princes favouring <hi>Hereticks</hi> are abſolv'd from their duty of Homage and Fealty, ſo long as thoſe Princes Continue in ſuch impiety. <hi>cap.</hi> 27.</q> And in the next <hi>Lateran</hi> Council unde<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Innocent</hi> 3. we have this moſt Loyal Conſtitution. <hi>cap</hi> 3. <q>That if a Temporal Lord, being commanded and warned by the Church, ſhould neglect to purge his <hi>Dominions</hi> of <hi>Hereſy,</hi> he ſhould firſt be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated by the <hi>Metropolitan</hi> and the other Biſhops of his <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince;</hi> and if within a year he refuſe to give ſatisfaction, let the <hi>Pope</hi> be informed of it, that he may declare his <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſſals</hi> free from their <hi>Allegiance,</hi> and expoſe his <hi>Dominions</hi> to be ſeized on by <hi>Catholicks,</hi> who, having thruſt out the <hi>Hereticks,</hi> might thence forward poſſeſs it without any Contradiction, and keep it in the true Faith: Yet let not this be prejudicial to the Principal Lord, on condition that he no way hinder this proceeding. And then they add, That the ſame
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:37787:11"/> Law is to be obſerved againſt thoſe, who have no principal Lords.</q> From theſe words <hi>Becanus</hi> inferres three things, and indeed they are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly contained in them. 1. <hi>That all Kings and Princes, whether Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream or Subordinate, are oblig'd by Oath to uſe their utmoſt endeavours for the Extirpation of thoſe Hereticks, which are condemned by the Church;</hi> and particularly thoſe, that deny <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> which Doctrine was here firſt determined. <q>2. <hi>That if, being admoniſhed by the Church, they neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect to do it, they are to be excommunicated by the</hi> Metropolitan, <hi>and o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r Biſhops of the</hi> Province. 3. <hi>That if they obey not within a year, they are to be deprived of their</hi> Kingdomes <hi>and</hi> Countries, <hi>and their</hi> Subjects <hi>abſolv'd from their Allegiance by the Pope.</hi> And therefore (ſaith he) all that acknowledge the <hi>Authority</hi> of this <hi>Lateran</hi> Council, ought to confeſs; <hi>That</hi> Kings <hi>and</hi> Princes <hi>may not only be excommunicated, but depoſed by the Pope.</hi> But this Council is received by all Catholicks; and there's good reaſon for it. 1. Becauſe it was General. 2. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe 'twas approved by the <hi>Pope,</hi> and received with the common Conſent of the whole World. 3. Becauſe 'twas the greateſt and moſt famous Council; For beſides the <hi>Pope,</hi> there were preſent in it two <hi>Patriarchs</hi> in perſon, and two by their <hi>Legats;</hi> ſeventy <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops,</hi> four hundred <hi>Biſhops,</hi> eight hundred <hi>Abbats</hi> and <hi>Priors;</hi> beſides the <hi>Legats</hi> of Emperors, &amp;c. <hi>Controv. Angl. p.</hi> 110—.</q> The Council of <hi>Conſtance</hi> alſo hath appear'd as zealous for this depoſing Doctrine; witneſs her Decree, <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 17. <q>All that ſhall hinder their great Patron <hi>Sigiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund</hi> from meeting with the King of <hi>Arragon,</hi> whoſoever they be, though <hi>King, Prince, Duke, Earl—.</hi> they are beſides Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, deprived <hi>ipſo facto</hi> of all their Secular Honour and Dignity.</q> And in the <hi>Bull</hi> of Pope <hi>Martin</hi> 5. read and approved in the laſt <hi>Seſſion</hi> of that Council, we find the ſame Doctrine aſſerted in theſe Words: <q>All Profeſſors of the Chriſtian and Catholick Faith, the Emperor, Kings, Dukes, Princes—are required to expel all <hi>Hereticks</hi> out of their Kingdomes, Provinces, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> according to the Canon, <hi>Sicut ait</hi> &amp;c. that is, the third <hi>Lateran</hi> Council, which hath been already mention'd.</q> And the Penalty is expreſſed towards the end of this <hi>Bull</hi> viz. <hi>That all Perſons favouring</hi> Hereticks, <hi>though</hi> Kings <hi>or</hi> Queens, <hi>or</hi> Dukes, <hi>or whatever other worldly</hi> Dignity <hi>they are poſſeſſed of, be not only excommunicated, but deprived of ſuch their worldly Goods and Dignities.</hi> What can be more fully expreſt? and yet our <hi>Country Gentleman</hi> hath the Confidence (or rather the Impudence) to tell the World, <hi>That the</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:37787:12"/> 
               <hi>Council of</hi> Conſtance <hi>hath condemn'd this King-depoſing Doctrine.</hi> I will add but one Council more, but that which our <hi>Adverſaries</hi> glorie moſt in <hi>viz:</hi> that of <hi>Trent,</hi> which hath paſſed this Decree. <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 25. <hi>c.</hi> 19. <hi>If the</hi> Emperor, King, Duke, Prince<hi>—ſhall grant in their Dominions a place for Duelling, they ſhal be excommunicated and deprived of the Dominion of the City, Caſtle, or place where ſuch a</hi> Duel <hi>hath been fought, if they were held in</hi> Fee <hi>from the Church.</hi> And that <hi>England</hi> is thus held ſince King <hi>John's</hi> Grant, all <hi>Catholicks</hi> affirm. And thus, <hi>Sir,</hi> I have Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced other kind of Proofs for this Poſition: <hi>That the Pope in certain Caſes may excommunicate and deprive Kings;</hi> than our Adverſary hath, or can produce againſt it. 'Tis ſo fully and frequently determin'd by their <hi>Popes</hi> and <hi>Councils,</hi> that I do not ſee how any Man can be a ſincere Papiſt, much leſs take Orders in that Church, and profeſs a diſ-belief of it. And this being ſo, I wiſh men would conſider, what little Aſſurance a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Prince can have of the Loyalty of his Catholick Subjects; ſince by their Religion they lawfully may, nay, in duty muſt (if an opportunity be preſented) riſe againſt him, fight with him, aſſaſſinate and murder him, when he's excommunicated by the Pope.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Gentleman</hi> in the next place endeavours to vindicate his Church from that bloudy Complotment, the <hi>Gun-powder-Treaſon;</hi> telling us. 1. That only a few inconſiderable Perſons, and Male-contents were engaged in it, or conſenting to it; which is moſt notoriouſly falſe. 2. That <hi>Maſſes</hi> or <hi>Prayers</hi> were then offered for the good Succeſs of the Cathol<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ck deſign, <hi>i. e. To obtain his Majeſties gracious releaſe from thoſe afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions they had long groaned under.</hi> p. 65. A pitieful come off, and moſt groundleſſe Suggeſtion; for what afflictions did they then groan under? King <hi>James</hi> hath long ago told the World. <q>That whatſoever was her juſt and merciful Government (meaning Q. <hi>Elizabeth)</hi> over the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> in her time, my Government over them ſince hath ſo farre ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded hers, in Mercy and Clemency, as not only the <hi>Papiſts</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves grew to that height of Pride, in confidence of my mildneſs, as they did directly expect, and aſſuredly promiſe to themſelves <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and equality with other of my Subjects in all things; but even a number of the beſt and faithfulleſt of my ſaid Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, were caſt in great fear and amazement of my Courſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings. How many did I honour with <hi>Knighthood,</hi> of known and open <hi>Recuſants?</hi> How indifferently did I give Audience and Acceſs to bo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ides, beſtowing equally all favours and honours on both Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions?—. <hi>Apolog. p.</hi> 253.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:37787:12"/>
            <p> Thus you ſee, if we may take the word of a King, that <hi>Maſſes</hi> were not offer'd to obtain his Majeſties gracious releaſe from ſore afflictions. Beſides, if this was the deſign, why were not the People acquainted with it? what danger could be ſuppoſ'd in telling them plainly, <hi>That Maſſes muſt be offered for a releaſe from their afflictions?</hi> King <hi>James</hi> in his <hi>Moni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Preface</hi> to all Chriſtian Monarchs <hi>p.</hi> 291 informs them, <q>That a great number of his <hi>Popiſh</hi> Subjects of all Ranks and Sexes, both men and Women, as well within as without the Kingdome, had a confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Notion, and an obſcure knowledge, that ſome great thing was to be done in that Parliament for the Weal of the Church, although for ſecrecies cauſe, they were not acquainted with the particulars; and that certain <hi>Forms</hi> of Prayer had likewiſe been ſet down and uſed for the good ſucceſs of that great Work.</q> Their <hi>Prieſts</hi> uſually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded their <hi>Maſſes</hi> and <hi>Oblatory Sacrifices</hi> with their Prayers for the good ſucceſs of the Catholick deſign. And theſe Verſes were made and uſed by <hi>Garnet.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Gentem auferte perfidam credentium de finibus,</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Chriſto laudes debitas perſolvamus alacriter.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And others pray'd thus: <hi>Proſper, Lord, their pains, that labour in thy Cauſe day and night; let Hereſyvaniſh away like ſmoak, let their Memory periſh with a Crack, like the ruin and fall of a broken Houſe:</hi> Speed in King James p. 892. Thus though the <hi>Deſign</hi> it ſelfe was underſtood by <hi>Few</hi> (for it was neither ſafe nor neceſſary to impart it to many) yet the <hi>Papiſts</hi> generally knew, that there was a <hi>Deſign</hi> in hand. And though there were but a <hi>Score,</hi> in the <hi>Treaſon,</hi> yet there appear'd <hi>Fourſcore</hi> in the <hi>Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> and it cannot be imagin'd, that ſo ſmall a Number could expect, without any other Aſſiſtance, to have made any great advantage of ſurpriſing the <hi>Lady Elizabeth.</hi> And that great numbers of Roman Catholicks be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Seas were acquainted with this horrid <hi>Treaſon,</hi> hath been abundantly prov'd by Many: nay, that it was carried on with the <hi>Privity</hi> and <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation</hi> of the <hi>Pope,</hi> is evident, both from <hi>Delrio diſq. Mag. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. and from what our Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> hath aſſerted from the voluntary Confeſſion of a <hi>Jeſuit</hi> viz. <q>That his <hi>Holineſs</hi> had order'd three <hi>Bulls</hi> to be in readineſs on the other ſide the <hi>Water,</hi> which were to be ſent over, and publiſhed in ſeveral parts of this Nation, ſo ſoon as the <hi>Blow</hi> was given.</q> 
               <hi>Tort. Torti.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>May we not then moſt juſtly charge their Church with this matchleſs <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon?</hi> ſince ſuch practices are agreeable to her Doctrines, and never any
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:37787:13"/> puniſhment inflicted by her on theſe <hi>Traytors.</hi> Nay, ſo far have they been from cenſuring theſe perſons, that two <hi>Jeſuits</hi> (principal Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors) were ſo kindly receiv'd at <hi>Rome,</hi> that one was made the <hi>Popes Paeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiary,</hi> and the othera <hi>Confeſſor</hi> in S. <hi>Peters</hi> at <hi>Rome.</hi> And <hi>Widdrington</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures us, that <hi>Garnets</hi> Name was inſerted into the <hi>Engliſh Martyrology;</hi> that his <hi>Bones</hi> were kept for <hi>Reliques,</hi> and his <hi>Image</hi> ſet over <hi>Altars,</hi> as of a holy <hi>Martyr. Append.</hi> p. 150. Such Honour have <hi>Traytors</hi> in the Roman Church: and yet this <hi>Gentleman</hi> hath the Impudence to affirm, <hi>That She abhors and puniſhes ſuch Traytors, as ſeverely as any</hi> Proteſtant <hi>can wiſh.</hi> p. 67. When ſome in the late Times had proceeded to ſuch a height of wickedneſs, as to take away the life of our <hi>Gracious Soveraign</hi> (which our Adverſary is pleaſ'd to object againſt us, though 'tis more then probable, that they were the <hi>Contrivers</hi> and <hi>Promoters</hi> of it, from what I urged out of Dr. <hi>Du Moulin</hi> (which was never anſwered by any) and others have atteſted) how did the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Nation</hi> groan, and were impatient till they could vindicate the Honour of our Religion and Countrie, not only by an execution of Juſtice on the immediate <hi>Actors,</hi> but by declaring in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament againſt the <hi>Principles</hi> that led them to it. Let this <hi>Gentleman</hi> ſhew us, that the like hath been done by the <hi>Court</hi> or <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Principles</hi> or <hi>Actors</hi> of this <hi>Gun-powder-Treaſon,</hi> and with my conſent, it ſhall never more be objected againſt them. And thus, <hi>Sir,</hi> I have conſider'd all that's material in his firſt <hi>Chap.</hi> except his bitter <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vectives</hi> againſt <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> which I reſerve for another place.</p>
            <p>I will wholly wave his ſecond <hi>Chap.</hi> in which there's not one true and pertinent word, excepting <hi>Bellarmin's</hi> Aſſertion, <hi>That</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>and not</hi> Rome, <hi>ſhall be the Seat of Antichriſt;</hi> for which ſeveral Fathers are cited by him: But moſt of them are ſuch, as he himſelfe <hi>(de Scriptor. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ.)</hi> confeſſeth to be Spurious. <hi>Sir,</hi> if you pleaſe to compare this <hi>Chap.</hi> with the Second <hi>Chap.</hi> in my Book, you I ſee the Honeſty of the Man, and find, that he hath not ſo much as mention'd (ſo farre is he from an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering) what is moſt material in it. What is there quoted out of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> and their own <hi>Authors,</hi> I avouch to be true, and can give an Ocular demonſtration of it, when he, or any other ſhall call upon me.</p>
            <p>Let us proceed to his third <hi>Chap.</hi> where <hi>(p.</hi> 101) he confidently affims, That we cannot know, which are the true Copy's of Gods Word, without the teſtimony of their Church; and conſequently cannot charge them with any Corruptions of Holy Scriptures. But the Learn'd Dr. <hi>Stilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleet</hi> hath ſufficiently prov'd. <q>That without this Teſtimony, we may be
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:37787:13"/> aſſur'd, there are no material Corruptions either in the Original <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew</hi> of the Old, or <hi>Greek</hi> of the New Teſtament <hi>viz.</hi> By the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent comparing the preſent <hi>Copy's</hi> with the moſt *Ancient <hi>M S S.</hi> by the obſervation of what Citations of Scripture are produced by thoſe of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>The ſame Courſe we<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Sixtus 5. <hi>and</hi> Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment 8. <hi>pretended to take in their Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Vulgar Latin. Praef. ad Bibl. Sixt. &amp; Clement</hi>
                  </note> the <hi>Fathers,</hi> who liv'd when ſome of thoſe <hi>Autographa</hi> were extant (as it is apparent ſome were in <hi>Tertullians</hi> time, and ſome tell us, that the Authentick <hi>Apocalypſe</hi> was preſerved in the Church of <hi>Epheſus</hi> in <hi>Honorius</hi> his time) by the diligence of the Primitive <hi>Writers</hi> in taking notice of the leaſt attempt for falſification or corruption of the Text; For when <hi>Marcion</hi> began to clip &amp; falſify the Text, <hi>Irenaeus</hi> preſently takes notice of it, and gives him a ſufficient rebuke for it: and ſo doth <hi>Tertullian</hi> and <hi>Epiphanius.</hi> So that whatever endeavours were made, they were preſently diſcovered; as that of the <hi>Arrians</hi> by S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> that of <hi>Tatianus</hi> his <hi>Monoteſſaron</hi> by <hi>Theodoret.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, it is obſervable, that among thoſe multitudes of <hi>Various Lecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> in the New Teſtament, of which <hi>R. Stephen</hi> made a Collection out of ſixteen <hi>M S S.</hi> of 2384. (which probably were occaſioned by the general diſperſion of Copies, and the multitudes of tranſcriptions by ſuch as were either ignorant or careleſs) yet there are none which are material (as <hi>Bellarmin</hi> hath confeſſed <hi>de Verb. dei. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. 7.) ſo as to entrench upon the integrity and authority of the Copies, as a rule of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Manners;</hi>
               </q> they are but <hi>Racings</hi> of the Skin, no <hi>wounds</hi> of any vital Part. &amp;c. <hi>Ration. Account</hi> p. 215—And <hi>Bellar.</hi> dares not ſay more of the <hi>Vulgar Latin.</hi> de V. D. lib. 2. c. 11.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Hebrew Doctors</hi> (ſaith this <hi>Gentleman</hi> p. 97. 98.) have corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Old Teſtament, and the <hi>Greeks</hi> the New. But the firſt is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely deny'd by their great <hi>Bellarmin</hi> (to paſs by others) and he urges five Arguments for it, the weakeſt of which our <hi>Adverſary</hi> is not able to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. <hi>de Verb. dei. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. And to the <hi>Tikkun Sopherim,</hi> produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by <hi>Porchetus,</hi> he anſwers, That the truth of it may be juſtly queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; ſince there's no mention of it, but in the <hi>Thalmud,</hi> which is a moſt fabulous Book. And thoſe <hi>Fathers,</hi> which were more Ancient than the <hi>Thalmud,</hi> make no mention of it. <hi>ibid.</hi> And to that Place, Cited out of <hi>Juſtin,</hi> he anſwers. <q>That <hi>Juſtin</hi> doth not ſay, that the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Text was corrupted by the <hi>Jews,</hi> but that of the 70 <hi>Interpreters.</hi> ibid. And concerning the Corruption of the New Teſtament, <hi>Bellarmin</hi> ſaith. That though <hi>Hereticks</hi> have endeavoured to deprave it (which is all that our Adverſaries Teſtimonies <hi>p.</hi> 98. do prove) yet Catholicks were
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:37787:14"/> never wanting, who diſcover'd and prevented thoſe Corruptions. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>That is,</hi> Irenaeus, Origen. Baſil, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe, <hi>and</hi> Hierom.</note> 
                  <hi>de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erbo dei lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 7.</q> And ſo much is affirmed by the great S. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> who writing againſt the <hi>Manichees,</hi> ſaith. <q>That with a deal of Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, or, to ſpeak mildly, with much weakneſs, they charged the the Scriptures to be corrupted;</q> and yet could not prove any corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by any Copies that are extant. <hi>de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tilit. Credend. cap.</hi> 3. And this <hi>Father</hi> lived almoſt 3 <hi>Centuries</hi> after <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> almoſt 2 <hi>Centuries</hi> after <hi>Orig<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n,</hi> almoſt 1. <hi>Century</hi> after <hi>Baſil</hi> and <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> and about 30 years after <hi>Hierom.</hi> And if the <hi>Hebrew</hi> and <hi>Greek</hi> Copies are ſo corrupt, as this <hi>Gentleman</hi> pretends, why did their Infallible Maſter, <hi>Clement</hi> 8. correct the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ulgar Latin</hi> according to the <hi>Original,</hi> in above 2000. places (as Dr. <hi>James</hi> hath obſerved) when the contrary Reading was eſtabliſhed by <hi>Sixtus</hi> 5. <hi>Praef. ad Bibl. Clem.</hi> And he might have added ſeveral thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands more, but <hi>conſulto immutata relicta ſunt ad offenſionem p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pulorum vitandam,</hi> they were purpoſely omitted, leſt the People ſhould take offence at them. <hi>ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Have not we then the greateſt reaſon, to rely on the <hi>Originals,</hi> when the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelf appeals to them, and reforms by them? for certainly the <hi>Hebrew</hi> and <hi>Greek</hi> are as obvious to us as them.</p>
            <p>Beſides, we are adviſed by the <hi>Ancients</hi> to go unto the <hi>Hebrew</hi> and <hi>Greek</hi> Fountains. <hi>As the purity of the Books of the</hi> Old Teſtament <hi>muſt be examined by the</hi> Hebrew, <hi>ſo the purity of the Books of the</hi> New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>muſt be examined by the Rule of the</hi> Greek Text. S. Hierom Epiſt. ad Lucinium. <hi>Men whoſe natural</hi> Language <hi>is</hi> Latin, <hi>have need of two other</hi> Tongues <hi>for the knowledge of the Holy Scripture, the</hi> Hebrew <hi>and the</hi> Greek; <hi>that they may have recourſe to the precedent</hi> (Hebrew <hi>and</hi> Greek) <hi>Copies, when the infinite variety of the</hi> Latin Interpreters <hi>brings ſome doubt.</hi> S. Auſtin lib. 2. de Doctrin. Chriſt. cap. 11. To theſe <hi>Amandus Pola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> hath added ſeveral both of the Greek <hi>and</hi> Latin <hi>Fathers</hi> Symphonia. Cathol. lib. 1. Nay we are obliged to this by their <hi>Pontifical</hi> Law: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t veterum librorum fides de Hebraeis voluminibus examinanda eſt, ita novorum veritas Graeci ſermonis normam deſiderat.</hi> Decret. pars 1. diſt. 9. c. 6.</p>
            <p>In the next place he endeavours to confute thoſe <hi>petty Inſtances</hi> (as he calls them) I urged againſt their <hi>Vulgar Latin.</hi> p. 105—.</p>
            <p>To the firſt <hi>viz. Gen.</hi> 3. 15. which the <hi>Vulgar Latin</hi> reads, <hi>Ipſa conte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret. She ſhall bruiſe thy head</hi> (contrary to the <hi>Hebrew Sept. Chald. Paraph.</hi> &amp;c.) He anſwers, that <hi>Victor, Alcimus, Avitus,</hi> S, <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> read it ſo. But the firſt, though Ancient, was not a <hi>Writer</hi> of any Note;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:37787:14"/> and <hi>Bellarmin</hi> gives this Character of him, <hi>That he was more addicted to the ſtudy of Rhetorick, than Divinity, and the Holy Scriptures.</hi> De Script. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. p. 124. The ſecond and third viz. <hi>Alcimus</hi> and <hi>Avitus,</hi> I never heard of before, and Challenge this <hi>Gentleman</hi> to produce them, or any <hi>Authentick Writer,</hi> that makes mention of them. I ſuppoſe he means <hi>Avitus Alcimus,</hi> urged by <hi>Bellarmin De V. D.</hi> who is an Author as ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure as the former.</p>
            <p>That S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> reads it ſo, is falſe. Indeed <hi>Philipus Montanus,</hi> who tranſlated <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> renders it, <hi>Ipſa,</hi> but he hath placed a <hi>Note</hi> in the <hi>Margin,</hi> that plainly ſhews the truer reading to be <hi>Ipſe.</hi> And ſo much is intimated in his Preface in <hi>Tom.</hi> 1. p. 8. and confeſſed by <hi>Pamelius, Annot.</hi> in <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Cyprian Teſtim. adverſus Judaeos n.</hi> 51. <hi>S. Auſtin Ambroſe, Gregory,</hi> and <hi>Beda</hi> have not only followed a corrupt <hi>Tranſlation</hi> of this Verſe, but alſo given us an <hi>Expoſition</hi> different, even from all both <hi>Popiſh</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Commentators, and contrary to the plain ſcope of the place.</p>
            <p>I could add as a further Proofe of this Corruption, the Teſtimony of <hi>Irenaeus adverſus Haereſ. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 38. and <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 78. <hi>S. Cyprian lib</hi> 2. <hi>Teſtim. adv. Judaeos. S. Hierom Quaeſt. Hebr. in Gen. Pope Leo Serm.</hi> 2. <hi>de Nativ. dom.</hi> who lived in the 5 Century. <hi>Iſidorus Peluſiota lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 426. who liv'd in the ſame Century. And <hi>Lucas Brugenſis</hi> aſſures us, that almoſt all the Fathers read <hi>Ipſe. Annot.</hi> 1. Nay, many <hi>Papiſts</hi> have acknowledged this Corruption. <hi>Melchior Canus Loc. Theol. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 15. <hi>Andradius Deferſ. Trident. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>Cardinal Cajetan in Gen. c.</hi> 3. <hi>Brixianus—.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 'Tis falſe ſaith (this <hi>Gentleman)</hi> the <hi>Vulgar Latin</hi> reads ſo abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely; for ſome <hi>Editions</hi> have <hi>(it)</hi> for <hi>(ſhe.) p.</hi> 107.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> If by <hi>Vulgar Latin,</hi> he means that of <hi>Sixtus</hi> 5. and <hi>Clement</hi> 8. which is the only authoriz'd <hi>Edition,</hi> 'tis moſt falſe, that any read <hi>(it.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it is time to conſider what he anſwers to <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. 13. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 16. And here he tells us. 1. <hi>That</hi> Primaſius (S. Auſtins <hi>Schollar) uſed the word</hi> (merit) <hi>in this very Text;</hi> as alſo <hi>Cyprian and others.</hi> 2. <hi>That the ſame</hi> Greek <hi>Word is thus tranſlated by us,</hi> Heb. 10. 29. 3. <hi>That if we confire this Word to the moſt rigid ſenſe</hi> viz. to obtain, procure<hi>—the Church will require no other</hi> merit. But. 1. This <hi>Gentleman</hi> doth not inform us, where <hi>Primaſius, Cyprian</hi> and others uſe the word <hi>(merit)</hi> in this Text; and I am as backward to believe him, as that <hi>Primaſius</hi> was S. <hi>Auſtins</hi> Schollar, who lived about 100. years after <hi>Auſtin,</hi> according to <hi>Bellarmin's</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:37787:15"/> computation. <hi>de Script. Eccleſ. p.</hi> 179. <hi>&amp;</hi> 246. 2. 'Tis moſt falſe, that the ſame <hi>Greek</hi> Word is thus tranſlated by us <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 29. And 3. As falſe, that the <hi>Roman</hi> Church by <hi>(merit)</hi> underſtands no more than <hi>to obtain, procure—. Concil. Trident. Seſſ.</hi> 6. <hi>can.</hi> 32.</p>
            <p>The other four <hi>Inſtances</hi> he paſſeth over, affirming p. 108. <hi>that they are confuted by</hi> Bellar. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>De V. D.</hi> whereas two of them are not ſo much as mention'd by <hi>Bellarmin.</hi> May we not juſtly wonder, that a man who profeſſeth Chriſtianity, nay, to be a Member of ſo excellent a Church, ſhould dare to aſſert ſuch notorious Falſities?</p>
            <p>From the <hi>Scriptu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es</hi> he proceeds to the <hi>Fathers</hi> p. 109. where he tells us. 1. <hi>That the</hi> Fathers <hi>have ſuffered infinite Corruptions by ignorant</hi> Tranſcribers, <hi>and the avarice of</hi> Book-ſellers. 2. <hi>That divers</hi> Fathers <hi>have writ erroneouſly, even in things of importance.</hi> 3. <hi>That ſome of them have been corrupted by</hi> Hereticks, <hi>in thoſe very things wherein they erred not.</hi> And then infers, <hi>That I muſt acknowledg, that the</hi> Roman <hi>Church in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting thoſe</hi> Original <hi>or</hi> Accidental <hi>Errours, executes her</hi> Office, <hi>acts a Careful</hi> part, <hi>and manifeſts her ſelfe the true</hi> Mother <hi>of Gods Children</hi> p. 111. And a little after aſſures his Reader, <hi>That the ſumme of my</hi> Accuſation <hi>is, that the</hi> Roman <hi>Church took theſe corrupt</hi> Fathers <hi>in hand, to make them ſpeak ſuitably to her</hi> Doctrines.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> you have already, ſeen what little reaſon we have to take this <hi>Gentlemans</hi> Word, and here no more is offer'd by him to ground our belief upon. We have charged their Church with the <hi>Alteration</hi> of ſeveral places in the <hi>Ancient Fathers;</hi> let this <hi>Gentleman</hi> prove thoſe places to have been corrupted either by <hi>Hereticks,</hi> or <hi>Tranſcribers,</hi> and we'l beg her pardon, and call them from henceforth <hi>Charitable Corrections.</hi> At preſent, we cannot but think it ſtrange, that the <hi>Fathers</hi> ſhould be ſo often printed by the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, with ſo much profeſſed care and fai<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hfulneſs (expreſſed in their <hi>Prefaces)</hi> and for ſo long paſs for <hi>Authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi> without one Syllable of any Corruption; and yet in this laſt <hi>Century,</hi> when <hi>Pro<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſtants</hi> began to read them, and urged from them ſo many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs <hi>Teſtimonies</hi> againſt their <hi>Novel Doctrines;</hi> they ſhould be charged with ſo many Corruptions by <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Tranſcribers.</hi> Here we muſt either condemn her former negligence, or ſuſpect her preſent honeſty: and whether of the two is obvious to any man.</p>
            <p>
               <q>But we cannot (ſaith he) ſuſpect the Ancient <hi>Fathers</hi> to be corrupted by their Church, to multiply Witneſſes for <hi>Popery;</hi> for thoſe very <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hers,</hi> whoſe <hi>Sayings</hi> or <hi>Corruptions</hi> She corrects, afford plentiful Proofs
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:37787:15"/> of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church's Faith from thoſe ſound parts, which are not call'd in Queſtion either by the <hi>Catholick</hi> or the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Church: witneſs <hi>Perron, Bellar.</hi> &amp;c. p. 116.</q>
            </p>
            <p>If all the <hi>Fathers</hi> be ſo expreſs for <hi>Popery,</hi> why then have their moſt eminent <hi>Doctors</hi> urged ſo many ſpurious Treatiſes (according to their own Confeſſions) and falſely alledged others? Let any Perſon look into <hi>Coc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius, Bellarmin, Caniſius</hi> &amp;c. (who trade moſt with the <hi>Fathers)</hi> and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine how many of thoſe places are convicted of <hi>Forgery</hi> by <hi>Baronius, Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar. Eraſmus, Sixtus Senenſis, Poſſevin</hi> &amp;c. and he muſt either deny what this <hi>Gentleman</hi> hath ſo confidently affirmed; or grant, that theſe great <hi>Champions</hi> and profound <hi>Scholars</hi> had been little converſant in the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi> For take thoſe ſpurious Treatiſes our, and their large <hi>Folio's</hi> would dwindle into little <hi>Quarto's.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis time to leave this, and paſs to his next <hi>Chap.</hi> where he lays down theſe three Propoſitions, <hi>which contain</hi> (and he might have added confirm) <hi>the contracted Venome and Quinteſſence of all my objected Caſes.</hi> p. 137—.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <q>That the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath univerſally degenerated from her wholeſome and Primitive uſe, and faithful diſpenſation of that moſt important Sacrament of <hi>Penance,</hi> ſeeing that contrary to the expreſs ſenſe of <hi>Antiquity</hi> ſhe daily and every where allows her Prieſts to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits evidently impenitent, wilfully and uncorrected, and daily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſing ſinners, and all ſorts without exception, to the Sacred benefit of Abſolution, and Communion: Not one <hi>Confeſſarius</hi> in ten Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand daring once in twenty years to make uſe of the retaining part of his power, for fear of incurring the ſhameful Cenſure of ſingularity.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <q>That the Primitive Practice of large and ſevere Injunctions is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warrantably perverted into that fatal indulging of a five Paters, or a Roſaries Pennance. A Cuſtom wofully experienced, to beget in ſinners a damnable preſumption, that Gods mercy is at the beck of the Courteous Confeſſor.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <q>That the univerſally eſtabliſhed Doctrine and uſe of Indulgences do expreſly thwart the Primitive ſenſe and Practice of that Juridical Part, lull Gods People into a preſumptuous ſecurity, and evacuate the Apoſtles Counſel, <hi>to work out our ſalvation with fear and trembling.</hi>
               </q> Now in vindication of his <hi>Holy Mother,</hi> three things are urged by him.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> 7. in the General Congregation at <hi>Rome,</hi> an. 1659. declared, <hi>That the Doctrines</hi> held forth by thoſe <hi>Caſuiſts,</hi> I menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd, <hi>are falſe, erroneous, ſcandalous, dangerous—</hi>p. 129.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:37787:16"/>
            <p> I confeſs this is as plauſably urged, as any thing I have met with in his whole Book; yet there's little in it, when all things are well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered. There had been for ſome years ſharp Conteſts between the <hi>Janſeniſts</hi> and <hi>Jeſuits</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and how Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> 7. ſtood affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted towards the latter, is clear from his ſevere Cenſures of ſeveral Books, that were written againſt them. In the Year 1657. he condemned the <hi>Provincial Letters.</hi> Congreg. 66. <hi>Sommaires des Declarations des Curez de Paris</hi> Congreg. 69. <hi>Jeſuitarum Atheiſmus detectus.</hi> Congreg. 84. <hi>Alphonſi de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>argas Toletani Relatio ad Principes Chriſtianos de Stratagem. &amp; Sophiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat. Politicis Societatis Jeſu—</hi>Congreg. 85. &amp;c. But this would not do the work; for the devout ſort of <hi>Catholicks</hi> (to uſe their own Words) were ſcandalized at thoſe Doctrines of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and <hi>Hereticks</hi> made their advantages of them: Therefore the Pope <hi>an.</hi> 1665. (not 1659. as our Adverſary affirms) cenſured certain Propoſitions, delivered by thoſe <hi>Caſuiſts,</hi> which were moſt inſiſted on by their Adverſaries, and offenſive to ſome devout <hi>Catholicks.</hi> We ſee now what 'twas, that put the Pope upon this Cenſure <hi>viz.</hi> the preſent State of Affairs in <hi>France,</hi> and not any diſ-like of the Doctrines; for had they been really diſpleaſing to his <hi>Holineſs.</hi> 1. He would have condemned the Authors of them, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited their Books; which was not done. 2. He would not have been ſo ſevere upon thoſe <hi>Doctors,</hi> that writ againſt them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He urgeth the ſevere <hi>Penances,</hi> impoſed by the Primitive Church upon notorious Offenders; of which he gives us <hi>(p.</hi> 146-) an <hi>Inſtructive Index</hi> (to uſe his own expreſſion) extracted out of <hi>Gratian</hi> &amp;c. And then aſſures his Reader, <hi>that theſe are enough to confront the</hi> Miniſter's <hi>pretended Liſt, and acquaint us with the careful and ſtrict Proceedings of thoſe beſt Ages of the Catholick Church.</hi> p150.</p>
            <p>But what is this to the preſent Church of <hi>Rome, which</hi> (as he told us before) <hi>hath univerſally degenerated from her wholeſom and primitive uſe, and faithful diſpenſation of that moſt important Sacrament of Pennance.</hi> The <hi>Roman</hi> Church, whilſt a <hi>Virgin</hi> was as ſevere, as now ſhe is become re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs: and what the <hi>Whore</hi> obtains for twelve pence, the honeſt <hi>Virgin</hi> had ſcarce granted for a Penance of twelve years. It was not then, as now at <hi>Rome,</hi> where <hi>Diſpenſations</hi> and <hi>Pardons</hi> are preſently got at a ſmall rate, according to their <hi>Taxa Cancellariae Apoſtolicae.</hi> This <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> ſeems to queſtion, whether ſuch a Book was ever printed, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by their Church. I thought this was ſufficiently clear'd from the pregnant Teſtimonies of their own <hi>Writers,</hi> which he neither hath, nor
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:37787:16"/> can object againſt. And for his further ſatisfaction, I will produce the Book, when he, or any other ſhall call upon me.</p>
            <q>But ſuppoſe (ſaith he <hi>p.</hi> 151.) the World had ſeen, or the Pope allow'd a Book of that Model, yet I am ſo juſt, as to clear the Church of that imputation; and to acknowledge, that not only ſome <hi>Sorbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts,</hi> but even the <hi>Inquiſitors</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> have ſtigmatiz<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d it.</q>
            <p>Certainly this <hi>Gentleman</hi> deſerves to be ſtigmatiz'd for an impudent Lyar. 1. <hi>I affirm</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that ſome</hi> Sorboniſts <hi>have condemned this Book.</hi> But where doth he find any mentiond by me, except <hi>Eſpencaeus,</hi> whoſe pious <hi>Cenſure</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Church is ſo far from approving, that the <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſitors</hi> have commanded it to be blotted out in their <hi>Expurga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Index</hi> p. 60. 2. <hi>I acknowledge</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that the</hi> Inquiſitors <hi>of</hi> Rome <hi>have ſtigmatiz'd it,</hi> This is as true as the former; for my words are theſe. <hi>And 'tis worthy of our Obſervation, that though the</hi> Inquiſitors <hi>of</hi> Rome <hi>have placed the</hi> Taxa Cancel. Apoſtol, <hi>in their</hi> Expurgatory Index, <hi>yet they except nothing againſt the Book, printed by the</hi> Romaniſts, <hi>but that only, which was lately put forth with</hi> Banks <hi>his</hi> Annotations, <hi>or which have been corrupted by</hi> Hereticks.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But why (ſaith this <hi>Gentleman)</hi> ſhould I quarrel with them for this, ſince our <hi>Spiritual-Swordmen,</hi> or <hi>Lay-Abſolvers</hi> do with approbation extract whole Eſtates out of the Peoples ſinnes?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> What may be done in the dark by ſome needy and coveteous Perſons, I know not; but that ſuch Practices are allow'd by the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> is moſt falſe. And let this <hi>Gentleman</hi> make good his Charge againſt theſe <hi>Spiritual Swordmen</hi> (as he calls them) and I dare undertake, that our <hi>Reverend Judges</hi> will make them Publick Examples. Other An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers I could return to this Objection, which for Brevity's ſake I will paſs over.</p>
            <p>3. To the laſt his Anſwer is, <hi>That he doth not apprehend, that their Church<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Doctrine and Sence of</hi> Indulgences, <hi>truly underſtood, can offer any ſcandal to the impartial Peruſer.</hi> p. 155. <hi>Sir,</hi> if you pleaſe to caſt an eye upon the incomparable Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet,</hi> and the Learned Dr. <hi>Brevint,</hi> who have lately diſcuſſed this Point, you'l ſee what little truth there is in this <hi>Gentleman's</hi> Aſſertion, concerning <hi>Papal Indulgences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I now leave this, and paſs on to his next <hi>Chap.</hi> where 1. He tells his Reader, <hi>that I have pickt up</hi> 3 <hi>or</hi> 4 <hi>of the leaſt Authentick, or rather doubtful Miracles, never as yet made uſe of by any Catholick Controvertiſt.</hi> p. 166. That theſe Miracles are more then doubtful, I take to be a
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:37787:17"/> great Truth But that they were never made uſe of by any <hi>Catholick Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trovertiſt,</hi> is moſt falſe; for ſome of them are urged by <hi>Bellarmin</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm their Doctrines. <hi>De Imagin. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 12. <hi>de Sacram. Euchar. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 8. To paſs by others. 2. He brings a <hi>Gordion Liſt of u<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Miracles in proof of ſeveral points of Catholick Faith.</hi> p. 167. But alas! the <hi>Authors</hi> he mentions, are either confeſſedly Spurious, as <note n="x" place="margin">Bellar. <hi>de Script. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ.</hi> p. 116. Ludovicus <hi>Vives in</hi> Auguſt.</note> 
               <hi>Athanaſius de Paſſione Imag. Chriſti.</hi> S. <hi>Auſtin de Civit. dei lib.</hi> 22. <hi>c.</hi> 8. &amp;c. or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly fabulous, as <hi>Gregorius Turonenſis, Paulus Diaconus, Paſchaſius,</hi> S <hi>Gregory, Beda</hi> &amp;c. or moſt falſely quoted, as I ſhall ſhew anon, <hi>Sir,</hi> if you deſire further ſatisfaction in this Point, be pleaſ'd to read the fore-mention'd Authors <hi>viz.</hi> Dr. <hi>Brevint</hi> and <hi>Stillingfleet,</hi> where you'l find the Queſtion truly ſtated, and enough to put any <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ober Man out of conceit with <hi>Romiſh</hi> Miracles.</p>
            <p>Nothing now remains, but that I give you a further account of this <hi>Gentleman's</hi> unworthy dealing in theſe falſe and ſlanderous <hi>Aſſertions,</hi> which make up a confiderable Part of his Book. As</p>
            <p>That the Roman Church hath taught Proteſtants all they know of Chriſtianity, <hi>Luther</hi> in <hi>Gal. p.</hi> 292. <hi>Wh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>taker Controv.</hi> 2. <hi>Q.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 14. Falſe. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>That all Chriſtians are free from the Obligation of the Mo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>al Law, <hi>Luth.</hi> in <hi>Gal. p.</hi> 46. 42. 49. 144. <hi>Calvin Inſtit. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 10. <hi>n.</hi> 5. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>c.</hi> 19. <hi>n.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4. All falſe.</p>
            <p>That the Church took it very ill, that Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> dealt ſo with the Emperor. <hi>Aquinas</hi> 22. <hi>Quaeſt.</hi> 12 <hi>Art.</hi> 2. Falſe. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 40.</note>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>Vincentius</hi> in his <hi>Speculum Hiſtor. lib.</hi> 15. <hi>c.</hi> 84. checkt that Fac<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Pope <hi>Gregory.</hi> Moſt Falſe.</p>
            <p>That the Catholick Biſhops in <hi>England</hi> with their Clergy declared to <hi>Q. Eliz.</hi> that it is not warrantable either by the Laws of God or Man, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 57.</note> to act againſt the allegiance, they owe to their Prince. <hi>Holinſhead</hi> Vol. 3. p. 1358—. That <hi>Parry's</hi> Fact was condemned by them. <hi>Holinſhead</hi> Vol. 3. p. 1385. and 1387. Falſe.</p>
            <p>That not above 13 <hi>Lay-men</hi> and 4 <hi>Jeſuits</hi> were either <hi>Actors</hi> in, or privy to the <hi>Gun-powder Treaſon.</hi> Baker p. 593. Falſe. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 64.</note>
            </p>
            <p>That this <hi>Plot</hi> was the <hi>Treaſurer's</hi> device, <hi>Osborn Mem of K. James.</hi> Falſe.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Popiſh</hi> Princes puniſhed the <hi>Albigenſes</hi> for their rebellious Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines againſt Princes. <hi>Illyricus</hi> Catal. Teſt. Ver. <hi>p.</hi> 735. and 755. And <note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 73.</note> for their actual Bebellions <hi>Oſiander Epitom. Cent.</hi> 16. p. 715. For which Biſhop <hi>Jewel</hi> diſowns them in the defence of his <hi>Apology. p.</hi> 48. All moſt Falſe.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:37787:17"/>
            <p> That <hi>Luther, Calvin,</hi> and other Principal <hi>Reformers</hi> are called the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 76.</note> 
               <hi>Flower</hi> of all precedent Doctors and Fathers; more knowing then all their <hi>Predeceſſors,</hi> yea, then the Apoſtles themſelves. <hi>Luther in Serm. de everſ. Hieruſal.</hi> p. 271. <hi>Beza Praef. in Nov. Teſt.</hi> The firſt Meſſengers of Truth. <hi>Jewel Apol. part</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>diviſ.</hi> 2. and <hi>Defence</hi> of <hi>Apol.</hi> p. 426. All falſe</p>
            <p>That among Chriſtians no Man ought to be Superior to another; that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 77.</note> none but Chriſt is Ruler over them. <hi>Luth. de ſeculari poteſt. Tom.</hi> 9. That he will diſturb the Publick Peace, and even confound and deſtroy the Prince himſelfe. <hi>Luth. Loc. Communes Claſſ.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 30. That we are exempted from all Human Laws by the Chriſtian Liberty, given us in Baptiſme. <hi>cap. de baptiſmo.</hi> All falſe.</p>
            <p>That notorious <hi>Rebellions,</hi> and barbarous <hi>Cruelties</hi> immediately follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 78.</note> upon theſe Doctrines by Proteſtants. <hi>Sleidan H<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt. lib.</hi> 22. p. 345. <hi>Oſiand. Cent.</hi> 16. p. 115. Falſe.</p>
            <p>That Earthly Princes diveſt themſelves of their power, when they oppoſe themſelves againſt God; and therefore 'tis fitter a Man ſhould ſpit in their faces than obey them, when they grow ſo ſawcy. <hi>Inſtit. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 20. and <hi>Comment in Daniel cap.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 39 <hi>cap.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 2. 25. All falſe.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Proteſtants</hi> advanced their wicked Principles in every Countrie <note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 79.</note> to an execution of the moſt horrid practices of inſolent Rebellion and Blood-ſhed &amp; Cruelty. In <hi>France</hi> for thirty years together. <hi>Oſiand. Cent.</hi> 16. p. 115 735. 599. <hi>Sutcliff Anſ. to a Supplic. Libel.</hi> p. 194. <hi>Hiſt. of the Civil Wars in France.</hi> In <hi>Germany Sleidan lib.</hi> 18. p. 263. In <hi>Swethland Chitraeus Chron. p.</hi> 74. 75. In <hi>Holland Oſiander Cent.</hi> 16. p. 801. 803. That they depoſed <hi>Ph<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lip</hi> K. of <hi>Spain</hi> from his Dominions in the <hi>Low-Countries. Oſiarder Cent.</hi> 16. <hi>p.</hi> 941. 805. That they violently excluded <hi>Sigiſmund</hi> K. of <hi>Sweden</hi> from his Crown. <hi>Oſiand. Cent.</hi> 16. p. 1115. and the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror</hi> from diverſe of his Rights in <hi>Germany.</hi> All falſe.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Luther</hi> affi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ms, That neither <hi>Auſtin,</hi> nor <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> nor any <note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 90.</note> 
               <hi>Doctor, Di<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ine—</hi>ſince the Apoſtles times, had ſo excellently inſtructed and confirmed Mens Conſciences, as he himſelfe had done. <hi>Luth in lib. ad ducem Georg.</hi> And that <hi>Calvin</hi> ſaith, That all the Ancient Fathers for 1300 years had been blindly led with Error. <hi>Inſtit. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 5. All falſe.</p>
            <p>That whether <hi>Antichriſt</hi> hath his ſeat at <hi>Rome</hi> or <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> yet even <note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 92.</note> then, neither the Church, nor Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall be <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> but both be perſecuted by him, and perſevere ſtill viſible and eminent. S. <hi>Auſtin de Civit. dei lib.</hi> 20 <hi>c.</hi> 8. <hi>&amp; in Pſal.</hi> 70. <hi>Calvin Inſtit. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>n.</hi> 12. All moſt falſe.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:37787:18"/>
            <p> That there was no viſible Church, but the Popiſh Church for 1260 <note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 95.</note> years before <hi>Luther. Napper upon the Revel.</hi> p. 145. <hi>Perkins upon the Creed.</hi> p. 400. <hi>and in his Reformed Catholick</hi> p. 307. All falſe.</p>
            <p>That the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Doctors have corrupted the Scriptures. <hi>Calvin In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 97.</note> 
               <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 13. <hi>n.</hi> 9 Falſe. That S. <hi>Hierom</hi> thought it not ſafe to recur to thoſe <hi>Hebrew Copies,</hi> where the <hi>Septuagint</hi> differs from them. <hi>In Epiſt. ad Gal. cap.</hi> 3. Falſe.</p>
            <p>That the firſt <hi>Reformers,</hi> and their <hi>Succeſſors</hi> have entirely condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 117.</note> and rejected the Fathers, both in general and particular, as blind, ignorant, and full of Errours. <hi>Luther de ſervo Arbitrio.</hi> p. 434. <hi>Calvin in Heb. c.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 9. <hi>Inſtit. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 12. <hi>n.</hi> 19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 30. <hi>Humſred, de vita Jeweli</hi> p. 212. <hi>Fulkes Retentive againſt Briſtow.</hi> p. 55. <hi>Wotton defence of Perk us</hi> p. 491. <hi>Whitaker contra duraeum lib.</hi> 6. p. 423. All falſe.</p>
            <p>That the ten Commandements belong not to Chriſtians. <hi>Luther Serm.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 124.</note> 
               <hi>de Moſe,</hi> and approved by <hi>Whitaker contra duraeum lib.</hi> 8. <hi>Sect.</hi> 91. <hi>Luther in Gal.</hi> cap. p. 227. That it is Hereſy to require good works to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Luth. Serm. de piſcat. Petri</hi> p. 154 All falſe in this <hi>Gentleman's</hi> ſence; for they conſtantly affirm, that the ten Commandements belong to Chriſtians as a Rule of life, and that good works are neceſſary to ſalvation.</p>
            <p>That the Church of <hi>England</hi> doth acknowledge in her <hi>Marginal</hi> Notes <note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 164.</note> upon <hi>Joh.</hi> 14. 12. <hi>That Believers in every Age have power to work Miracles.</hi> Falſe.</p>
            <p>That infinite Miracles have been wrought by the Reliques of Saints. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 168.</note> 
               <hi>Whitaker contra duraeum lib.</hi> 10 p. 866. Falſe.</p>
            <p>That the real Preſence is confirm'd by many Miracles, acknowledged <note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 169.</note> by Dr. <hi>Humfrey</hi> in his <hi>Jeſuitiſme</hi> p. 2. <hi>rat.</hi> 5. p. 626. and <hi>Centuriſts. Cent.</hi> 4. <hi>col.</hi> 431. And that famous one in the Town of <hi>Knoblock</hi> an. 1510. is related as a certain truth by <hi>Oſiander <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent.</hi> 16. <hi>cap.</hi> 14. p. 28. All moſt falſe.</p>
            <p>That ſeveral Miracles are confeſſed by the <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uriſts,</hi> to prove the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 170.</note> 
               <hi>Maſs</hi> to be a true Sacrifice, <hi>Purgatory</hi> and <hi>Prayer</hi> for the dead. <hi>Cent.</hi> 6. <hi>Col.</hi> 819. <hi>&amp; Cent.</hi> 7. <hi>Col.</hi> 577. All moſt falſe.</p>
            <p>That the Miracles wrought by S. <hi>Oſwald,</hi> and others are approved by <note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 179.</note> 
               <hi>Holinſhead</hi> in his <hi>Chron.</hi> Vol. 1. p. 115. 170. Falſe.</p>
            <p>That the formentioned Miracles, and many others of the ſeventh Age, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 180.</note> are acknowledged by the <hi>Centuriſts Cent.</hi> 7. cap. 10. Col. 533. and <hi>Oſian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Epitom.</hi> Cent. 7. Falſe.</p>
            <p>That many undoubted Miracles were wrought in the 8. 9. 10. and 11. Ages in confirmation of the uſe of Images, the Veneration of holy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:37787:18"/> Invocation of Saints, and the Sacrifice of the Maſs, offered for the Living and the Dead. <hi>Oſiander Epit. Cent.</hi> 8. p. 47. and 92. <hi>Item</hi> p. 24. 25. The <hi>Centuriſts Cent.</hi> 8. cap. 13. <hi>Cent.</hi> 9. cap. 13. <hi>Oſiander Epit.</hi> Cent. 9. p. 63. All moſt falſe.</p>
            <p>That the Miracles of S. <hi>Dunſtan</hi> are recorded and approved by <hi>Holin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhead</hi> Vol. 1. 165. and others in the ſame Age by the <hi>Conturiſts Cent.</hi> 10. cap. 13. and <hi>Oſiander Epit. Cent.</hi> 10. p. 125. All moſt falſe.</p>
            <p>That the Miracles wrought in the Eleventh Age by S. <hi>Anſolm, O<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>o.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 181.</note> and others, in confirmation of the Sacrifice of the Maſs, and Invocation of Saints, are confeſſed by <hi>Oſiander Epit. Cent.</hi> 9. 10. 11. p. 213. Falſe.</p>
            <p>That infinite Miracles were done by <hi>Malachias</hi> in the twelveth Age, whereof ſome were ſeen and acknowledged by many hundreds of People. <hi>Holinſhead Chron.</hi> p. 55. Falſe.</p>
            <p>That many Miracles were done by S. <hi>Bernard,</hi> and acknowledged by the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 182.</note> 
               <hi>Centuriſts Cent.</hi> 12. col. 1634. 1635. 1649. and <hi>Oſiander Cent.</hi> 12. lib. 4. cap. 6. p. 310. And that theſe moved <hi>Whitaker</hi> to give him the juſt Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of a true Saint. <hi>De Eccleſ.</hi> p. 369. All moſt falſe.</p>
            <p>He further tells us, That ſignal Miracles were wrought in the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Age by S. <hi>Dominick,</hi> and S. <hi>Francis,</hi> even while they were preaching againſt the <hi>Albigenſian</hi> Errours, whom Satan had ſeduced to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thoſe known Doctrines of Gods Church <hi>viz. Purgatory, Prayers for the dead, Confeſſion, Extream Unction, the Popes Authority, Images, Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions—</hi>And in the next page aſſures us, <hi>That the Miracles wrought in the</hi> 15<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 
               <hi>Age, are admired and reverenced by</hi> Proteſtants <hi>themſelves</hi> But for both theſe we muſt take his bare word; and how can he in reaſon ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect this from us, who ſtands convicted of above a hundred notorious Lyes?</p>
            <p>Perhaps here you'l ſay, That the <hi>Printer</hi> has miſtaken many of the <hi>Quotations;</hi> and therefore we cannot in juſtice charge them on the <hi>Author:</hi> Or that he hath taken them upon the Credit of other Writers.</p>
            <p>But to the firſt I anſwer. 1. That the <hi>Printer</hi> cannot be charged with any miſtake in reference to many, nay moſt of the <hi>Quotations,</hi> I have mention'd. 2. That about two Months ago I writ to this <hi>Gentleman</hi> (and have great aſſurance that my Letter came to his Hands) and deſired him, that, if there were any <hi>Errata's</hi> in the <hi>Citations,</hi> he would be pleaſed to ſend me a corrected Book, and it ſhould be faithfully return'd: But to this day I never heard from him.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:37787:19"/>
            <p> And to the ſecond <hi>Plea</hi> viz. That he hath taken theſe <hi>Citations</hi> upon the <hi>Credit</hi> of other <hi>Writers</hi> (which I believe to be a great truth) I anſwer, That to take things upon truſt in Controverſial Points, argues much weakneſs and imprudence; but to do this, and not give his Reader the leaſt intimation of it, argues great unfaithfulneſs and diſhoneſty, that will not admit of any Excuſe. And to evidence his great Proficiency in this Catholick Vertue, I could give you many other Inſtances; but for Brevity's ſake I'le mention but one, which you may find <hi>p.</hi> 190. and will appear moſt notorious upon your comparing of it with <hi>p.</hi> 127. of my Book. Here he confidently tells the World, <hi>that all that the Biſhops of</hi> Bononia <hi>(as they are alledged in the laſt page but one of my Book) do affirm i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, That private mens conſtructions of the Bible have raiſed great ſtorms and differences, and that the Doctrines preached by Chriſtians (or the Romiſh Church) ſe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m contrary to thoſe contained in the Bible.</hi> But the advice of thoſe Biſhops to the <hi>Pope</hi> was related by me in theſe words: <hi>Let that little ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, which is wont to be read in the</hi> Maſs; <hi>and more then that let no Mortal, be allow'd to read, For ſo long as men were content with that little, your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs ſucceeded according to deſire; but quite otherways ſince ſo much of the Scriptures was publickly read. In ſhort, this is the Book, which above all others, hath raiſed theſe ſtorms and ten peſts. And truly, if any one read that Book (the</hi> Scriptures) <hi>and obſerve the</hi> Cuſtomes <hi>and</hi> Practices <hi>of our Church, will ſee that there is no agreement betwixt them, and that the</hi> Doctrine, <hi>which we preach, is altogether different from, and ſometimes cont<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ry to that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Bible.</hi> Now can any Man pick out of theſe Words, or will any one, but a frontleſs Romaniſt, affirm, that the ſenſe of them is, <hi>That private mens conſtructions of the Bible have raiſed great ſtorms and differences,</hi> &amp;c. I grant, we are to put the moſt favourable conſtruction upon another's Words and Actions; Yet I take that <hi>Caution</hi> in their <hi>Canon-Law</hi> to be extravagant, <hi>viz. That if a P<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt ſee one of their Prieſts k<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſing a Woman, he's bid to believe, that the Prieſt is only giving her good Counſel:</hi> For though Charity be can did and ingenuous, yet 'tis not blind and block<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh. And that their Charity muſt have theſe debaſing Qualifications, who endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to excuſe this <hi>Gentleman,</hi> is obvious to any. I hav found him guilty of about an hundred and fifty falſe <hi>Quotations,</hi> and obſerved near halfe that number, that are wholly impertinent, beſides many that I have not time to examine. <hi>Sir,</hi> if theſe <hi>Roman Factors</hi> dare publiſh ſuch notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Falſities</hi> to the World, we may eaſily gueſs what pretty <hi>Stories</hi> they
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:37787:19"/> tell their deluded <hi>Proſelytes</hi> in ſecret. Let us commiſerate their Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who have committed their Souls to the Conduct of theſe <hi>Spiritual Mountchancks,</hi> and admire Gods diſcriminating Mercy, who hath deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered us from their Fatal deluſions.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> I am</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt Obliged and faithful Servant I. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
